<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great Britains jubile, or, A rural present to His Royall Majesty, my gracious, renowned and admired soveraign, Charles the IJd of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, King, defender of the faith, &amp;c. in divers panegyricks and poems on several objects, persons, and occasions : relating to his sacred person, and progress / by Lancelot Reynolds, Gent.</title>
            <author>Reynolds, Lancelot.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57191</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12388006</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12388006</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60904</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57191)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60904)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 225:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great Britains jubile, or, A rural present to His Royall Majesty, my gracious, renowned and admired soveraign, Charles the IJd of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, King, defender of the faith, &amp;c. in divers panegyricks and poems on several objects, persons, and occasions : relating to his sacred person, and progress / by Lancelot Reynolds, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Reynolds, Lancelot.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 111 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Vaughan for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:1"/>
            <p>Great Britains JUBILE; OR A Rural Preſent; to his Royall <hi>Majeſty,</hi> my Gracious,
renowned, and Admired <hi>SOVERAIGN,</hi> Charles the IJ<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. OF <hi>Great Britain, France,</hi> and
<hi>Ireland,</hi> King. <hi>Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</hi> In divers <hi>Panegyricks,</hi> and
<hi>Poems,</hi> on ſeveral Objects, Perſons, and Occaſions: relating to his <hi>ſacred
Perſon,</hi> and Progreſs.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Si Deus nobiſcum, quis contra nos, </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 8.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By LANCELOT REYNOLDS, Gent.</p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>Roger <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aughan,</hi> for the Authour, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:2"/>
            <p>THE ROYAL OAK REVIVED: SOME Branches thereof Illuſtrated, AND SOVERAIGN MAJESTY PROTECTED.</p>
            <p>THat Royal Oak that kept my Gracious King, Continue green, in Summer, Winter, Spring:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:3"/>
            <head>TO HIS SACRED MAJESTY Charles the II.</head>
            <head type="sub">By the Grace of God King of Great <hi>Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
DEFENDER OF THE FAITH, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread and Admired Soveraign;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe whole world cannot parallel ſuch a Miracle of Mercy, as the Lord hath vouchſafed in your
gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and miraculous Preſervation, and Reſtorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, beyond many mens expectation of your
Sacred Majeſty, unto us your obedient Subiects, and to be inveſted in your dear and Royal
Fathers Throne, without effuſion of blood. For which unſpeakable mercy and bleſsing, let us
magnifie the grand mercy of our good God, for his mercy endureth for ever, and render our
thankfulneſs from the ground
<pb facs="tcp:60904:4"/>and bottom of our hearts. As <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> the Perſian King, did kindly accept
of a handful of fair water from his poor Subject <hi>Sinates:</hi> And another great Monarch, of a
handful of roots from his poor Subject: So my hope is, that your Royal Majeſty will be pleaſed,
graciouſly to accept this Paper-preſent, proceeding from the heart, hand, and pen, of your
moſt Loyal Subject, who doth truly reverence and honour your Sacred Perſon. Part of theſe
poor unpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht lines were intended againſt your Majeſties coming to the Right Honourable
<hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Poulet</hi> of <hi>Henton Saint George,</hi> within the County of
<hi>Sommerſet;</hi> and to the Honourable Colonel <hi>Francis Windham</hi> at <hi>Trent.</hi> I
am truly ſenſible of mine inabilities to anſwer expectation, and therefore do humbly ſue
for your gracious pardon: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the ancient of days, to add many years unto your preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
life. The Lord make your Sacred Majeſty a ſpecial choice inſtrument of his glory, that you
may reign gloriouſly here, and have a Crown of Immortal Glory hereafter; for the obtaining
whereof, your Majeſty ſhall have the most fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and hearty prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties most humble, loyal, and faithful Subject. Lancelot
Reynolds.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60904:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Royall, <hi>famous</hi> Oak, <hi>no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> revived;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His</hi> Maieſties <hi>Court obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur'd for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ime:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some conſtant, faithful Courtiers, deſcribed;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Both now praiſed be God most bright do ſhine.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>FOr to begin, with <hi>Wor'ſters</hi> bloudy Fight</l>
               <l>It would almoſt amaze the <hi>World</hi> to write:</l>
               <l>Where they did kill and ſlay without meaſure;</l>
               <l>And car'd not for their lives, but their Treaſure.</l>
               <l>The Fight was hot, and bloudy was that day:</l>
               <l>It was indeed, a deadly mortall Fray.</l>
               <l>Oh may we to our <hi>God</hi> moſt thankfull be</l>
               <l>Who did preſerve our <hi>King,</hi> our all in Thee.</l>
               <l>'Tis beyound Mans thoughts, and admiration,</l>
               <l>His Eſcape, and bleſt Preſervation!</l>
               <l>Of my <hi>Soveraignes Perſon</hi> and Deare Life,</l>
               <l>Which comforts doth conveigh, to Man and Wife,</l>
               <l>And Children likewiſe, doth thereof pertake,</l>
               <l>Oh let us love him, for his own Names ſake</l>
               <l>He is our <hi>Soveraigne Lord</hi> that doth protect,</l>
               <l>Friends, and En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mies, that do not him reject;</l>
               <l>His Lawfull power, and his Command;</l>
               <l>That doth <hi>Gods</hi> word obey, and firmly ſtand.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:60904:5"/>
               <l>At <hi>Worster,</hi> at that great and cruel fight,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>royal Sov'raign</hi> then was forc'd to flight:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> knew not where to go, to ride, or run,</l>
               <l>To keep himſelf from being quite undone.</l>
               <l>Our <hi>bleſſed Saviour</hi> did an <hi>Oak</hi> provide:</l>
               <l>His <hi>ſacred Perſon,</hi> for a time to hide:</l>
               <l>Until Brave <hi>Lord Wilmot,</hi> did him remove:</l>
               <l>Whereby he ſhew'd his Zeal, and faithful love.</l>
               <l>Oh bleſſed <hi>Oak,</hi> that ſhel red my <hi>dear Lord:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who alwayes truſted in Gods holy Word:</l>
               <l>From ſight of wicked, and ungodly men:</l>
               <l>Not fit for Earth, but for a <hi>Lyons Den.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If that they meant my <hi>Sov'raign</hi> to deſtroy,</l>
               <l>They would thereby, three Kingdomes much annoy.</l>
               <l>When our <hi>gracious Lord</hi> was in diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>God did ſupport him in his heavineſſe.</l>
               <l>To his <hi>dear Lord,</hi> then he did make his mone,</l>
               <l>Who did him comfort, though he were alone.</l>
               <l>Gods <hi>Angel</hi> guided him ſtil in his way;</l>
               <l>In a moſt ſafe, and hollow tree to ſtay.</l>
               <l>Oh, When, <hi>dear Lord,</hi> ſhall my weak eyes be bleſt,</l>
               <l>To ſee that woman, gave my <hi>King</hi> ſweet reſt:</l>
               <l>When his ſad heart with ſorrow did abound,</l>
               <l>So rare eſcape, on Earth, can ſcarce be found.</l>
               <l>The hollow <hi>woods,</hi> the <hi>Trees</hi> did comforts bring,</l>
               <l>Unto our <hi>gracious,</hi> and admired <hi>King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did ever <hi>God</hi> for any <hi>King</hi> ſo work?</l>
               <l>In time of horrid danger; for to lurk,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60904:5"/>
               <l>In ſo obſcure, and ſolitary place;</l>
               <l>Where Gods <hi>Vicegerent King,</hi> by Gods high grace;</l>
               <l>When griefs, fear, horror, did his ſoul affright,</l>
               <l>My <hi>royal Soveraign</hi> in the dark ſome night:</l>
               <l>Where one bleſt man, by hap, did him attend;</l>
               <l>And prov'd to be his true, and faithful friend.</l>
               <l>God bleſſe him ſtill, in body and in ſoul,</l>
               <l>That he may ne're but for his ſinnes condole.</l>
               <l>The ſhady <hi>woods,</hi> and <hi>trees,</hi> comforts afford</l>
               <l>Unto our <hi>ſoveraign King,</hi> and <hi>gracious Lord.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>woods</hi> and <hi>trees,</hi> a <hi>Lane</hi> God did provide:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Lane</hi> adorn'd with vertue, and with grace;</l>
               <l>O're whelm'd with joy, to ſee her <hi>Sov'raigns</hi> face:</l>
               <l>To free him from his fears, and dangers deep;</l>
               <l>Secure his perſon, and his life to keep,</l>
               <l>In bleſſed ſafety, free from mortal harmes;</l>
               <l>From bloudy men, claſp'd in his <hi>Saviours</hi> armes.</l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Almighty</hi> did, his precious ſoul, protect;</l>
               <l>And will alwayes, his faithful, bleſt elect.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">1623.</note>When that <hi>royal P. Charles</hi> went into <hi>Spain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reſolving, then, a Princeſſe for to gaine:</l>
               <l>For ſafety of his life, he chang'd his name:</l>
               <l>And travel'd with great <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Buckingham.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There names they thought fit for to chang;</l>
               <l>That they might ſee far Countreys ſtrang:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Will,</hi> and <hi>Tom Smith,</hi> were then their names,</l>
               <l>Which might ſeem ſtrange unto King <hi>James,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60904:6"/>
               <l>That <hi>gracious, wiſe,</hi> and <hi>royal King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who to fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nations peace did bring,</l>
               <l>Read <hi>Wilmot</hi> forward, backward, and then finde;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Tom</hi> ready, perfect in your minde.</l>
               <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Subjects chang'd their love, king <hi>Charles</hi> his name;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Royal C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aries</hi> is after call'd <hi>William.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A name of <hi>Conquerour</hi> it did foretell;</l>
               <l>A happy <hi>Omen,</hi> that he ſhould do well:</l>
               <l>To live to <hi>conquer,</hi> overcome at laſt;</l>
               <l>Pardon Offences, forgive what is paſt.</l>
               <l>To live to <hi>reign,</hi> to be a <hi>glorious King;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Much joy, and happineſſe, to three <hi>kingdomes</hi> bring:</l>
               <l>In a fourth alſo he hath a good ſhare;</l>
               <l>And likewiſe doth a <hi>Sovereign</hi> title bare;</l>
               <l>My <hi>Sovereign</hi> conquer'd not by ſword, but love;</l>
               <l>God did his words and actions well approve.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>On our</hi> gracious <hi>KING his</hi> feigned <hi>Name</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When he rode</hi> diſguiz'd <hi>with Miſtriſſe</hi> Lane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>William,</hi> Conquerour of this Nation;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the worker of our ſalvation.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi> did labour to preſerve our king;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lane</hi> ventured life, him for to ſafety bring:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord,</hi> puts all his truſt;</l>
               <l>Abounding in mercy, able for to ſave:</l>
               <l>Majeſty dejected, from untimely grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:60904:6"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Wiſe men, and great, have changes in this life;</l>
               <l>In youth, and age, avoid all mortal ſtrife:</l>
               <l>Lift up your heart unto your <hi>Creator;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Loſe no time, of <hi>Heav'n</hi> to be Pertaker:</l>
               <l>In time of <hi>life,</hi> think on that night of <hi>death;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All that are born, are ſurely born to dy;</l>
               <l>Man lives below, may your <hi>ſoul</hi> mount on high.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wealth, nor honour, can keep us from grim <hi>death,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Jewels, nor gold can much prolong our breath;</l>
               <l>Lord, we muſt all drink of <hi>Deaths</hi> bitter cup,</l>
               <l>Low brought by ſin, yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> can raiſe us up,</l>
               <l>In glory bright, above the <hi>ſtarry</hi> sky,</l>
               <l>Amidſt the glorious <hi>Saints</hi> your foul w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l fly.</l>
               <l>Mongſt holy <hi>Martyrs</hi> to the <hi>Trinity.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whiles I did live in heart of <hi>Oake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I fear'd not <hi>death,</hi> nor yet his ſtroake.</l>
               <l>Laid low by ſad event of War,</l>
               <l>Lifting my heart to God above,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> my Saviours love,</l>
               <l>Advanced by his King, his God;</l>
               <l>Made to eſcape his Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While I did live in ſorrow for my king;</l>
               <l>It joy'd my heart, when brave <hi>Monck</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d him bring</l>
               <l>Lare, better then never, for him to raign:</l>
               <l>Long live king <hi>Charles,</hi> in glory to remain,</l>
               <l>In health, and happineſſe, unto the end</l>
               <l>And never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>and in need of <hi>earthly</hi> friend;</l>
               <l>Mongſt Saints and Angels after this life ſpend.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60904:7"/>
            <head>On <hi>his Sacred Majeſty CHARLES STUART, King of</hi> ENGLAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>Chriſt now hath brought you, to your fathers throne:</l>
               <l>Heav'n hath his ſoul, to you we make our mone:</l>
               <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, and armes, with him are gon to grave;</l>
               <l>Royalty remains yours, his Crown to have:</l>
               <l>Lord, after this life, bring your <hi>ſoul</hi> to bliſs;</l>
               <l>Eternal Joy, and endleſs Happineſs;</l>
               <l>Saints <hi>robes</hi> put on, of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his righteouſneſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soaring aloft by <hi>Meditation,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Truth to maintain, and <hi>Reformation:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Up ready, to uphold Gods word,</l>
               <l>A <hi>gracious King,</hi> and <hi>Soveraign Lord;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Right <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> in word, and deed;</l>
               <l>Tyrants power, by your hand is freed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Calamities are paſt, and gone;</l>
               <l>Heav'ns pow'r hath fixt you on your Throne:</l>
               <l>Arts now embrace, let Warrs depart,</l>
               <l>Rejoyce in God, with all your heart:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Heav'ns</hi> King guide you, in your wayes,</l>
               <l>Eternally, your good God to praiſe;</l>
               <l>Sanctity, you will practice, all your dayes.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:60904:7"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Sweet influence, <hi>dear Lord,</hi> doth flow from thee,</l>
               <l>Truth, Peace, Love, <hi>heroick</hi> Clemency:</l>
               <l>Unanimous Providence, Gods Decree;</l>
               <l>Again to raiſe your <hi>ſacred</hi> Majeſty;</l>
               <l>Raiſing You up, above your Family,</l>
               <l>To do ſervice, for your grand King, on high.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cares, and great <hi>Troubles</hi> do attend a <hi>Crown:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Heav'ns King protect You, put your En'mies down:</l>
               <l>A happy chang we have now liv'd to ſee,</l>
               <l>Royal king <hi>Charles</hi> in perfect Majeſtie:</l>
               <l>Let us lift up our hearts to God on high,</l>
               <l>Ever to bleſſe, praiſe, and perform his will,</l>
               <l>Serve our <hi>dread Sov'raign,</hi> be obedient ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sanity from your bleſt hand doth proceed;</l>
               <l>The gentle touch of your fair hand doth breed;</l>
               <l>Unto the ſick Patient quick cure, and eaſe;</l>
               <l>A happy Cordial for ſo ſad Diſeaſe:</l>
               <l>Royal Kings have ſuch vertue in their touch;</l>
               <l>The like, no other man, can do ſo much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When our <hi>happy Parliament</hi> did ordain,</l>
               <l>To fetch our <hi>bleſſed Soveraign</hi> home again;</l>
               <l>And <hi>valiant Montague</hi> pointed to bring,</l>
               <l>The Perſon of our <hi>royal gracious King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>royal Fleet,</hi> committed to his hands,</l>
               <l>To wait him home, who ruleth divers Lands:</l>
               <l>Grief did then vaniſh, and ſoon paſſe away;</l>
               <l>Then did begin our happy <hi>Halcion Day.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60904:8"/>
            <head>On that <hi>Mirrour</hi> of <hi>loyaltie,</hi> and admired <hi>Gentlewoman,</hi> Miſtreſs
Jane Lane.</head>
            <head type="sub">His <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> moſt <hi>faithful, humble,</hi> and <hi>obedient</hi>
Subject.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jane, gracious</hi> your Name doth ſignifie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> good Name doth the Owner dignifie.</l>
               <l>Nature and rich Grace did contend in thee,</l>
               <l>Ever to comfort <hi>royal Majeſtie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>faithfull love</hi> thee did invite,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> gracious <hi>Lane</hi> a comfort for to be;</l>
               <l>Nature and Grace did in you take delight,</l>
               <l>Even to live, or dye, for's <hi>Majeſtie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jngenious <hi>Lane,</hi> you did your wits awake,</l>
               <l>Add greateſt vigour for your <hi>Sov'raigns</hi> ſake;</l>
               <l>No wit, nor p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licy you did omit,</l>
               <l>Endeavours, of your own, proper, and fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lanes</hi> numberleſſe are, in <hi>Great Britains</hi> Land,</l>
               <l>Amongſt them all none did more firmly ſtand;</l>
               <l>None in <hi>fair England,</hi> better could accord:</l>
               <l>Enter a way to pleaſe her <hi>ſacred Lord</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:60904:8"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Judicious Jane,</hi> thy wayes were firm, and good,</l>
               <l>An honourer ſtill of the <hi>Royal</hi> blood;</l>
               <l>Nights may ſeem pleaſant, for to tell of thee,</l>
               <l>End, and begin, of's <hi>Bleſſed Majestie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Led on by <hi>Angels,</hi> for to guide thy way,</l>
               <l>Above moſt Names, may <hi>Lane</hi> bare the ſway;</l>
               <l>No Night approach, but be a <hi>Halcion Day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>E're for your carrying, your <hi>Dear Lord</hi> away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jn ſorrow, and in joy, I'le bear my part,</l>
               <l>And love my <hi>Sov'raign</hi> with my <hi>ſoul,</hi> and heart;</l>
               <l>No worldly thing ſhall part my <hi>loyal</hi> love,</l>
               <l>E're to maintain, and ſtill to him approve.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laud</hi> ſtill that Name, that holy Name of God,</l>
               <l>Abide in Vertue, ſhun his 'venging rod;</l>
               <l>None, <hi>None but Chriſt,</hi> did that brave <hi>Martyr</hi> ſay;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eternity crown</hi> you, on your laſt day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jnſpire your heart, with knowledg, and with grace,</l>
               <l>Attend at laſt to ſee thy Soveraigns face;</l>
               <l>New ſhall your Name and actions then be found,</l>
               <l>E're for to praiſe, and make his Praiſe reſound.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lament you did, for your good <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>King;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Adventured your life, him ſafe to bring;</l>
               <l>Nere to the ſea his Perſon to convey,</l>
               <l>Expecting him to rule another day.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60904:9"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jane</hi> was that bleſſed name, gave me my life,</l>
               <l>And being in the World, t'enjoy a Wife</l>
               <l>Nature, and Grace caus'd her my life to ſave,</l>
               <l>Ere comforted me, and kept me from grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Leaſt in my infancy I ſhould periſh,</l>
               <l>A Nurſe did provide, me for to cheriſh;</l>
               <l>Nature being weak, made choice of a Nurce,</l>
               <l>Ev'n me to luckle, though to me the worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A bleſſed <hi>Jane</hi> did our <hi>dear Father</hi> feed;</l>
               <l>In a ſad time, when 'twas of greateſt need;</l>
               <l>The <hi>happy Father</hi> of my Native Land,</l>
               <l>Who firm in his faith, did for ever ſtand:</l>
               <l>As he was firm, and conſtant to the <hi>Lord,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And carefull to obey his <hi>ſacred Word;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So did the Lord in his due time provide,</l>
               <l>A faithfull, <hi>valiant Champion,</hi> him to guide;</l>
               <l>And to conduct unto His Fathers throne;</l>
               <l>Where all ſad hearts are heard, who make their moan.</l>
               <l>Our wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> doth hear Cauſe juſt;</l>
               <l>Do righteous things, before he turn to duſt.</l>
               <l>God grant him <hi>Neſtors years,</hi> yea long to live</l>
               <l>And many <hi>Godly Acts,</hi> and <hi>Lawes</hi> to give.</l>
               <l>God make my <hi>Sov'raign</hi> happy in a Wife,</l>
               <l>Vertuous, firtile, grand comfort to his life:</l>
               <l>Give him a <hi>royal,</hi> and moſt faithful <hi>Queen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As ever was in <hi>fair great Britain</hi> ſeen.</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:60904:9"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maſter JOHN DANVERD,</hi> for your precious lines,</l>
               <l>Valu'd in part equal to golden <hi>Mines:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I will in praiſe and honour of you write,</l>
               <l>Which of <hi>our Soveraign</hi> did ſuch things indite:</l>
               <l>Thou doſt recount his dangers that are paſt;</l>
               <l>Of your <hi>royal Maſter,</hi> and <hi>King</hi> at laſt:</l>
               <l>Which doth now give the Nation great content;</l>
               <l>That d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, in th'acting, make him to lament:</l>
               <l>To ſee, at that time, his diſaſtrous fate:</l>
               <l>Brought low, by fatall war, his Princely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tate.</l>
               <l>But God, in mercy, did at laſt him bring,</l>
               <l>To be our <hi>Soveraign Lord,</hi> and <hi>Gracious King.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>John, Gracious</hi> your name doth import,</l>
               <l>On things <hi>divine</hi> thy thoughts reſort;</l>
               <l>Heav'ns glory thy ſoul mounts to ſee,</l>
               <l>Night of <hi>Death</hi> paſt in joyes to be,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dan,</hi> one of <hi>Jacobs</hi> bleſſed Sons;</l>
               <l>An Angel will thy ſoul convey;</l>
               <l>Nature ſubdu'd, Grace bears the ſway.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Verd</hi> waxing <hi>green,</hi> in vertue bright,</l>
               <l>Eternal Day, when paſt thy night.</l>
               <l>Raiſe up thy ſoul above the sky,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dauverds</hi> heart loves true Majeſtie.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:60904:10"/>
            <head>Upon the <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>joyfull News</hi> of <hi>his ſacred Majeſty,</hi> King
Charles <hi>the</hi> II<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>his returning into</hi> England; <hi>And</hi> proclaiming <hi>of
him,</hi> King <hi>of</hi> England, Scotland, France, <hi>and</hi> Ireland.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>REturn, return brave <hi>Prince,</hi> from <hi>fertile France;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fair</hi> England long hath lain in a ſad trance.</l>
               <l>From <hi>rich Holland</hi> our <hi>King</hi> will ſoon arrive:</l>
               <l>Make joyfull hearts, and many will revive;</l>
               <l>Paſſe o're the Sea, and come to <hi>Dover</hi> Town:</l>
               <l>T'enjoy his <hi>Crown</hi> with <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Renown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our Noble <hi>Phenix,</hi> he will come at laſt;</l>
               <l>And put a period to our griefs, are paſt.</l>
               <l>When he ſhall land, in faithfull, fruitfull <hi>Kent;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Many brave Nobles will be thither ſent:</l>
               <l>For to conduct our <hi>Royal, Gracious Prince;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Enemies actions will them then convince.</l>
               <l>Your <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed Parliament</hi> will act,</l>
               <l>What they think fit, about that horrid fact,</l>
               <l>Of putting your <hi>Royal Father</hi> to <hi>death:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And taking from him, his moſt <hi>precious breath.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They did ſo ſoon ſever's <hi>immortal Soul;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That moſt o'th <hi>kingdome</hi> did with greif condole:</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60904:10"/>
               <l>Oh may ſad, <hi>horrid Warre</hi> now paſſe away;</l>
               <l>And when you come, appear a <hi>haleion day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May <hi>mirth,</hi> and <hi>gladneſſe,</hi> be in place of <hi>grief,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And yeild the moſt remoteſt <hi>ſoul</hi> relief.</l>
               <l>Your Fathers <hi>ſpirit</hi> ſoar'd unto the skie;</l>
               <l>His <hi>Meditations</hi> were profound, and <hi>high:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>active Genius</hi> it did ſoar aloft;</l>
               <l>Who truſted in's Saviour, whoſe ſoul he bought.</l>
               <l>Welcome <hi>Royal Charles,</hi> unto your <hi>Fathers</hi> Throne;</l>
               <l>His <hi>Friends</hi> do <hi>live,</hi> though he be <hi>dead</hi> and gone.</l>
               <l>They do <hi>revive,</hi> though in Vault he lies <hi>dead:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And will ſupport you; What more can be ſed:</l>
               <l>With Life, and Fortunes, as long's they draw <hi>breath:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And will continue conſtant, till their <hi>death.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chriſt will conduct you to your <hi>Fathers Court;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where Great, and Small, will thither then reſort.</l>
               <l>Times various are, in turning of Mans <hi>ſtate:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Moſt happy thoſe, that are Regenerate.</l>
               <l>After many ſorrows, joy doth come at laſt;</l>
               <l>And ſeems greater, when dangers are overpaſt.</l>
               <l>The <hi>King</hi> will come, to joy ſad hearts of Men:</l>
               <l>That joy I cannot full expreſſe by pen.</l>
               <l>When that, with <hi>Triumph,</hi> he ſhall be landed here;</l>
               <l>Many <hi>brave, wiſe, Noble Men</hi> will appear;</l>
               <l>And wait upon his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and it guard;</l>
               <l>Our <hi>heavenly</hi> King give them their reward,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Royal Sun</hi> will ſhine in <hi>Albions</hi> Iſle;</l>
               <l>And make things clear, whom envy doth defile.</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60904:11"/>
               <l>Obſcure, and darken, with their <hi>envious breath:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which nothing will work of, but <hi>time</hi> and <hi>death.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whiles <hi>Britains Iſle</hi> doth <hi>flouriſh,</hi> and wax green:</l>
               <l>Your <hi>famous Actions,</hi> ever ſhall be ſeen;</l>
               <l>Renown your Name, unto after Ages:</l>
               <l>In well writ Books, admir'd and learn'd Pages:</l>
               <l>Regain the Honour of our <hi>brave Nation;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And bring it into ſome better Faſhion.</l>
               <l>News is now come, <hi>king Charles</hi> proclaim'd ſhall be:</l>
               <l>God give him happineſſe, and proſperitie:</l>
               <l>Long <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> that He may ſafely <hi>raign;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And prove to be a ſecond <hi>Charlema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gn.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May great <hi>Jehovah</hi> bleſſe your <hi>Majeſtie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>royal Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Poſterity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Pardon, great <hi>Prince;</hi> my failings, and accept:</l>
               <l>A Mite inſtead of Pounds, for my great Debt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60904:11"/>
            <head>The <hi>faithful CHAMPION,</hi> and <hi>admired</hi> SUBJECT.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>On his</hi> Excellency <hi>General MONCK,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And thoſe brave Valiant, and Religious Men,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who was a mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to bring king CHARLES agen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To rule and raign in fair</hi> Great <hi>BRITAINS Iſle:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let us praiſe God, that he doth on us ſmile.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THe time is come, that joyes men for to ſee</l>
               <l>A Supreme Power of high <hi>Soveraignity:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our Famous <hi>Engliſh Nation</hi> ſtrive to bring,</l>
               <l>Faire, and rich Preſents to their <hi>royal King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Joy doth abound, and ſtir up their brave minde:</l>
               <l>For to expreſſe their Love, and Nature kind.</l>
               <l>They do bethink the time of his abſence:</l>
               <l>And poſt unto him, with <hi>golden</hi> Preſents;</l>
               <l>There's nothing that they have they think too dear;</l>
               <l>The worthy <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and noble <hi>Peer;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Sun</hi> doth ſhine, and yeild a pleaſant <hi>light:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This new great chang, doth give mens hearts delight.</l>
               <l>Behold how God doth worke in his due time;</l>
               <l>To bleſſe, and comfort the good True Divine;</l>
               <l>Yea, and all other men, we hope beſide;</l>
               <l>That in his ſacred <hi>truth</hi> doth firm abide.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:60904:12"/>
               <l>It is the hand of God, hath this thing wrought:</l>
               <l>It was his Son, our Soules moſt dearly bought.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Monck</hi> mounted high, to bring his <hi>Soveraign</hi> home;</l>
               <l>That Power, was deriv'd, from God alone.</l>
               <l>Gods <hi>Spirit</hi> mov'd him to do ſuch a thing;</l>
               <l>Well pleaſing to Gods People, and the <hi>King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It was not in the ſimple power of Man;</l>
               <l>For to obtain, nor in their power to skan:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Finger</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> did it direct,</l>
               <l>And brought the ſame, at laſt, to good effect.</l>
               <l>No Gold, or Silver, could the ſame obtain:</l>
               <l>So rare, ſo Rich, and unexſpected gain.</l>
               <l>A <hi>King,</hi> to <hi>rule</hi> a <hi>Religious Nation;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In <hi>Godly order,</hi> is a <hi>ſtately Faſhion.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thoſe happy Men</hi> that ſtudied this <hi>Great work,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God ſtill preſerve from <hi>Pagan,</hi> and from <hi>Turk:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I mean, from all ſorts of vile, <hi>wicked Men:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Too long for to recount, with my weak Pen.</l>
               <l>We want a <hi>Homer,</hi> to ſet forth thy <hi>Fame:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Noble Actions,</hi> and thy <hi>Mighty Name.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The high,</hi> and <hi>gracious Work,</hi> thou didſt archive,</l>
               <l>Will <hi>make</hi> thy <hi>Fame,</hi> even after <hi>death,</hi> to <hi>live.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <hi>Julius Coeſar,</hi> can his <hi>fame</hi> advance,</l>
               <l>So <hi>high</hi> as <hi>thine,</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or in <hi>France.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Stout <hi>Hannibal</hi> could not do ſuch a <hi>Thing:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To bring from <hi>Forraign</hi> Parts, his <hi>Soveraign King:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In ſuch a manner, and you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d no blood:</l>
               <l>Perform an Act on, could not be withſtood.</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60904:12"/>
               <l>Rich <hi>Croeſus</hi> could not purchaſe, with all his wealth,</l>
               <l>So rare a <hi>cordial,</hi> for <hi>Englands</hi> perfect <hi>health:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Treaſure</hi> was exhauſted, and grown low:</l>
               <l>In great Diſtreſſe, and knew not where to go.</l>
               <l>Many people did want, and cry for bread:</l>
               <l>And knew not, by their Labour, to be fed:</l>
               <l>Moſt <hi>Trades</hi> were barren, and grown very poore:</l>
               <l>And knew not how for to encreaſe their ſtore.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe bleſſed Men</hi> have us'd a ſtrain above:</l>
               <l>That will, moſt juſtly, merit faithfull Love.</l>
               <l>In all things then, let us humbly ſubmit,</l>
               <l>Unto his hand, that knowes what is moſt fit</l>
               <l>Our Maker made us, and he knowes our mould:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> paid our ranſome: we are bought and ſold.</l>
               <l>In brief, let us <hi>love</hi> God, <hi>honour</hi> our King:</l>
               <l>Give them the praiſe, that did him ſafely bring,</l>
               <l>From <hi>Forraign Parts,</hi> into our <hi>Native Land.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And, in <hi>true Faith,</hi> ſee that you firmly ſtand.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, then due prayſes render,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To</hi> God that hath reſtor'd their <hi>Faiths Defender.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh that I could <hi>immortalize</hi> thy <hi>Name:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And build a ſtately <hi>Structure</hi> to thy <hi>fame.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I would crect a ſtately <hi>Monument:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To continue, till time on <hi>Earth</hi> be ſpent:</l>
               <l>In mind, it ſhould exceed <hi>Romes Capitol:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For him that was ſo wiſe, Majeſticall:</l>
               <l>As <hi>high,</hi> and <hi>famous Capitol</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which might continue, till the <hi>Day of Dome.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:60904:13"/>
               <l>Or <hi>famous Coloſſus,</hi> that did Ships guide;</l>
               <l>His Lamp did light them, not to ſail aſide</l>
               <l>Or <hi>ancient, famous, Mauſoles</hi> Tombe:</l>
               <l>Beyond that ſumptuous <hi>Capitol</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or rare, brave <hi>Pyramids</hi> of <hi>Egypts</hi> Land;</l>
               <l>Or what might be fram'd by a Mortal hand.</l>
               <l>Could erect a Pile, of that great Store:</l>
               <l>For to continue while time were no more.</l>
               <l>All theſe, I wiſh, I could perform by pen;</l>
               <l>Brave <hi>Monck,</hi> and his Friends ſtill might live 'mongſt Men</l>
               <l>God will advance, continue your rare Name:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Angels</hi> ſound the <hi>Trump</hi> of thy great Fame.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Soladine,</hi> after all his brave Conqueſts paſt,</l>
               <l>Carryed but a Shirt unto his Grave at laſt.</l>
               <l>God bleſſe the King,'s High Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That they may love, and act with joynt conſent.</l>
               <l>When that your Gracious Soul away ſhall flie,</l>
               <l>The Glorious <hi>Angels</hi> guide it to the skie.</l>
               <l>When that your body ſhall be laid to ſleep,</l>
               <l>In Mother Earth, your duſt, moſt ſafe, ſhall keep.</l>
               <l>When Crowns and honours ſhall turn to an Urn,</l>
               <l>May Glory, after Death, be your Return.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60904:13"/>
            <head>On that <hi>Worthy, Accompliſhed</hi> Gentleman, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Thomas Mayhew.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>TRanſcendent Mayhew,</hi> for your <hi>royal</hi> Lines,</l>
               <l>Writ with a quill, pluckt from an Angells wing;</l>
               <l>Shall flour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh and wax green, in future times:</l>
               <l>For writing the welcome, of our deareſt King.</l>
               <l>Who is the Fountain of our Bliſs, our All:</l>
               <l>His Royal Perſon, high Emperiall.</l>
               <l>Of <hi>brave Mayhews</hi> Writing let's take a veiw;</l>
               <l>So rich, ſo rare, and of ſo fair a hew.</l>
               <l>Mount up, <hi>rare Mayhew,</hi> get <hi>Promothean</hi> Fire:</l>
               <l>To warm thy wings, and mount high by deſire.</l>
               <l>Thou doſt beſtir, thy golden, nimble Pen:</l>
               <l>To exhilerate the ſad hearts of men.</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>hew</hi> is glorious, in the Moneth of <hi>May:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Flowers, then are fair, freſh, look full gay:</l>
               <l>Flowers then are ſweet, pleaſant, rare, and new.</l>
               <l>Nones fairer have expreſſed, then <hi>Mayhew.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His dainty Fancy, and his golden Pen,</l>
               <l>Doth eq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l, if not exceed, moſt of Men,</l>
               <l>Thy Noble Spirit, it doth ſoar aloſt;</l>
               <l>Chriſts precious blood, thy pure ſoul, dearly bought,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Genius</hi> is ſublime, and mounteth high:</l>
               <l>Thy bleſſed Saviour will thee dignifie.</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Muſe</hi> doth ſoar up high, and elevate:</l>
               <l>Thy thoughts are profound, and do contemplate,</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:60904:14"/>
               <l>On things <hi>ſacred, ſumpt'ous, rare,</hi> and <hi>divine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>which ſhall continue, as long's <hi>Mortal time.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Maynew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is <hi>brave, ſublime,</hi> and <hi>royal Pen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eetly <hi>pleaſe,</hi> delight the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>Men.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am is high, and lofty is his Spirit;</l>
               <l>Which, one Day will, the <hi>ſpacious</hi> Heaven inherit.</l>
               <l>Long may you live, to write on divers things:</l>
               <l>On high <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Kings.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>High Matters, do well become, thy brave Pen:</l>
               <l>To ſolace rich <hi>Saints,</hi> and the beſt of Men</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mayhew</hi> doth fill he minde, with wonders great:</l>
               <l>In writing in ſuch manner, brave, compleat.</l>
               <l>The more thou doſt extol, and praiſe my King:</l>
               <l>The more I will thee praiſe, thy goodneſſe ſing.</l>
               <l>My weak Pen cannot, expreſſe, thy rare worth:</l>
               <l>A <hi>Homer,</hi> or <hi>Lucan,</hi> muſt it ſet forth,</l>
               <l>In perfect Colours, and thy Noble hew:</l>
               <l>Who can expreſſe, and write like <hi>brave Mayhew.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The very luſtre, of thy famous Name,</l>
               <l>Shall ſtill preſerve, thy rare, and Noble Fame.</l>
               <l>Let Angels ſound the Trump of thy high praiſe:</l>
               <l>For to continue beyond length of Dayes.</l>
               <l>Let Time be weary, for to meaſure times:</l>
               <l>So long, or longer, dure thy Famous Lines.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Angels</hi> ſing, the praiſes, of your Verſe;</l>
               <l>Which I, weak man, not able to Rehearſe.</l>
               <l>I wiſh and pray, that long, long, thou mayſt live:</l>
               <l>More <hi>Royal Verſes,</hi> to my <hi>Soveraign</hi> give.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:60904:14"/>
            <head>Upon the Sight of King Charles <hi>the</hi> II. <hi>his</hi> Picture, <hi>at the
Honourable</hi> Colonel, Sr. <hi>JOHN DRAKE,</hi> Knight, <hi>and</hi> Baronet, <hi>his</hi>
Houſe <hi>at</hi> Trill, <hi>in</hi> Devon.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF that the <hi>Shadow</hi> doth the <hi>minde</hi> content:</l>
               <l>Much more the <hi>Subſtance, pure, excellent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If that the Shadow, doth ſuch Reverence move:</l>
               <l>What will the Subſtance, with dear, <hi>faithfull Love!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If that the Shadow do but repreſent:</l>
               <l>How doth the Subſtance give moſt ſweet content!</l>
               <l>Though's hair be black, yet his Soul's white within:</l>
               <l>God keep his Body ſafe, his Soul from ſin.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and <hi>Immortal King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>CHARLES <hi>REX,</hi> to the higheſt <hi>honours</hi> bring.</l>
               <l>May he be <hi>happy,</hi> 'bove all Kings on Earth:</l>
               <l>Eternally happy after his death.</l>
               <l>I want <hi>Apelles</hi> Pencil, for to limb:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Homers</hi> famous Pen to paint out him.</l>
               <l>His <hi>royal</hi> Head, the watch-Tower of the Sences</l>
               <l>His ſweet <hi>Clemency</hi> pardons great <hi>Offences.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Eyes, though black, yet do moſt purely ſhine:</l>
               <l>His <hi>Knowledge</hi> high, like a <hi>Rare Divine.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60904:15"/>
               <l>His Eye of Providence, did long foreſee,</l>
               <l>The Effects of <hi>Times,</hi> and how they would be.</l>
               <l>His precious Eares, do ever love, to hear,</l>
               <l>Gods <hi>ſacred Word,</hi> which he doth hold moſt dear.</l>
               <l>His Smelling, ſweet things, doth revive his ſences:</l>
               <l>God, and our <hi>gracious King</hi> pardons offences:</l>
               <l>Yet to a Lover, nothing ſmells more ſweet;</l>
               <l>Than M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtriſs brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, when lip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and hearts do meet.</l>
               <l>His Taſte is pure, ſweet with Delectation;</l>
               <l>By Faith he feeds on Chriſt, for his Salvation.</l>
               <l>His Feeling's quick, and all his Sences good;</l>
               <l>His greateſt <hi>Treaſure,</hi> is <hi>Christs precious blood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His rubie Lips, though ſhadowes, I could kiſs;</l>
               <l>His Soul, and Body, God for ever bleſs:</l>
               <l>His Lilly white hand, I have kiſs'd before;</l>
               <l>And hope hereafter, to kiſs it once more.</l>
               <l>His <hi>golden Crown,</hi> doth by his ſweet ſide lie:</l>
               <l>After this life, may his Soul mount on high;</l>
               <l>Above the Sphears, and bright ſtar ſpangled Skie:</l>
               <l>To live with's Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> eternally.</l>
               <l>I'le pray, that he may long, and happy raign:</l>
               <l>And after <hi>death,</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> e're remain.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60904:15"/>
            <head>On's <hi>ſacred MAJESTIES</hi> CORONATION: <hi>The bleſt Precurſor of</hi>
Reformation.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THis Day, <hi>my Gracious Soveraign</hi> crown'd ſhall be;</l>
               <l>And will ſhow forth his <hi>Royal Majeſtie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God bleſſe that <hi>reverend hand,</hi> that <hi>crown's</hi> our <hi>King</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let us praiſe God, that he did ſafely bring</l>
               <l>Him hither, for to ſit, on's Fathers <hi>Throne;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It was the handy work of God alone.</l>
               <l>Famous <hi>Albemarle</hi> was the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of our <hi>royal Comforts,</hi> and high Content;</l>
               <l>Cncurring with the <hi>bleſſed Parliament.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God give him a <hi>happy,</hi> and a <hi>bleſſed Boon;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Comfort his <hi>bleſt Soul,</hi> Morning, Night, and Noon.</l>
               <l>Rejoyce this Day, <hi>Great Britains</hi> KING <hi>is crown'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Long may he live,</hi> and ever be renown'd.</l>
               <l>Oh let his <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> ſo tranſcend;</l>
               <l>That Every <hi>Nation</hi> may become his Friend.</l>
               <l>Defend Him <hi>Lord,</hi> who is <hi>Faiths Defender;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Strengthen Brethren, and <hi>confirm</hi> the <hi>Tender.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Protect him, <hi>Lord,</hi> who art the <hi>Worlds Protector.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From's Enemies, and every ill Projector,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Famous</hi> King <hi>Charles,</hi> let his Name ever Ring;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Royal,</hi> brave <hi>Anthems</hi> to his praiſes ſing.</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:60904:16"/>
               <l>The Nobles, and the Gentry flock to ſee,</l>
               <l>This famous, far renown'd Solemnitie.</l>
               <l>Oh what a Royal, Stately, and brave ſight:</l>
               <l>To ſee the King, with's Nobles, ſhine moſt bright:</l>
               <l>In Radicant manner, with that luſter ſhine,</l>
               <l>With Royal Glory, and with Lords Divine:</l>
               <l>Royall attended with a Princely Train:</l>
               <l>Not inferiour to brave, Great <hi>Charlemain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To that Famous <hi>Abby</hi> Our Soveraign came:</l>
               <l>Bravely attended with his Men of Fame.</l>
               <l>The Noble Lords all came in their order,</l>
               <l>In their Rich Robes, and moſt ſtately border:</l>
               <l>Coller of Eſſes, their George, and brave things:</l>
               <l>Fit, well becoming the high ſtate of Kings.</l>
               <l>The Bells did ring: Conduits run wine: all rejoyce:</l>
               <l>Expreſſing it, both with hand, heart, and voice:</l>
               <l>When he had heard a Sermon preached there:</l>
               <l>He was conducted to an ancient Chair:</l>
               <l>Where many Kings have been crown'd in this land</l>
               <l>God ſtill preſerve tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bleſſed, happy hand.</l>
               <l>But firſt, his brave <hi>grand Champion</hi> claim'd the <hi>Crown</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For our true Soveraign, of ſo great renown.</l>
               <l>They did acknowledge him to be <hi>true</hi> Heir:</l>
               <l>And did conduct him to that Royal Chair:</l>
               <l>Being the next great Prince of <hi>Royal Blood:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who will undoub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed do this Nation good.</l>
               <l>The Nobles then did performe their Duty:</l>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omage to their Gracious Soveraign Lord.</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:60904:16"/>
               <l>They put their hands unto the Royal Crown.</l>
               <l>And venture Life, and ſtate for his Renown.</l>
               <l>The Reverend Biſhops preach to him Gods Word:</l>
               <l>Which he moſt ready is for to obey.</l>
               <l>God keep his Perſon ſafe, both Night and Day.</l>
               <l>They preſent themſelves at his Royall Feet.</l>
               <l>His Sacred Perſon did them kindly greet.</l>
               <l>And moſt lovingly did kiſs their Right Cheek:</l>
               <l>In gallant manner, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n order meek.</l>
               <l>A Ring's put on, as wedded to a Wife.</l>
               <l>Great God of Heaven preſerve him all his life.</l>
               <l>Our King's anointed with moſt precious Oyl.</l>
               <l>May he his Enemies overcome, and quail.</l>
               <l>Then was the <hi>Crown</hi> put on his ſacred <hi>head.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let Angels guide him, till his ſoul be fled.</l>
               <l>And afterwards convey his Soul to bliſſe;</l>
               <l>To Glory, and Eternall happineſſe.</l>
               <l>Great Acclamations made, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Trumpets ſounded, and with Ecchoes ring.</l>
               <l>Let Bonfires blaze, and Bells out loud now ring:</l>
               <l>To ſhow our Love unto our Graciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King.</l>
               <l>The Great, and Glorious God aſſiſt my Pen;</l>
               <l>To write of my Soveraign, the beſt of Men;</l>
               <l>That Rules, and Raigns in Fair <hi>Great Britans</hi> Iſle.</l>
               <l>Let's praiſe the Lord, that he doth on us ſmile.</l>
               <l>The <hi>King of Kings</hi> give Power for to write,</l>
               <l>On him, in home he taketh great delight.</l>
               <l>No Angel will forbid quills from his wing;</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:60904:17"/>
               <l>To write in praiſe, of my <hi>renowned Ring.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some bleſſed, holy, precious <hi>Angel</hi> bright;</l>
               <l>Give me a Quill from his rare Wing, to write;</l>
               <l>What I do for my <hi>Dear Soveraigns</hi> ſake.</l>
               <l>My drow ſie Muſe, O Lord do thou awake.</l>
               <l>My mind will be content, my heart at eaſe;</l>
               <l>If ſome <hi>fow Lines</hi> may <hi>my Dear Soveraign</hi> pleaſe.</l>
               <l>This <hi>royal Solemnity</hi> being paſt;</l>
               <l>They did return in order, all at laſt.</l>
               <l>It was a <hi>ſtately Sight,</hi> there for to ſee,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Nobles</hi> paſſe in Rank, in their Degree.</l>
               <l>But b'ing <note n="*" place="margin">115 miles</note> far diſtant, cannot now relate,</l>
               <l>The manner how they rode, or walkt in ſtate.</l>
               <l>It was my happineſſe, for to ſee</l>
               <l>King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> crowned for to be.</l>
               <l>In the ſame manner I do apprehend,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thu was perform'd;</hi> and ſo do draw to'n end.</l>
               <l>Wiſhing, praying, my <hi>Soveraign</hi> long may live</l>
               <l>More worthy Lawes, unto his <hi>Subjects</hi> give.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord</hi> give my <hi>Soveraign,</hi> a <hi>Vertuous Queen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As ever was in fair <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſeen.</l>
               <l>Grant him a happy <hi>Iſſue,</hi> proſperous <hi>Raign;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Long here on Earth, with Saints for to remain.</l>
               <l>After this Mortal Crown ſhall paſſe away,</l>
               <l>Give an immortall Crown, ne're to decay.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In the</hi> highe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <hi>heav'ns,</hi> where the Saints excell;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In that</hi> bleſt <hi>Place</hi> may his <hi>Soul</hi> ever <hi>dwell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60904:17"/>
            <head>On His <hi>moſt Excellent MAJESTY,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> His
exſpected coming to the Honourable <hi>Colonel FRANCIS WINDHAM, his</hi> Houſe at
<hi>Trent.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WElcome <hi>Dear Soveraign,</hi> welcome to <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May it yield <hi>your Highneſs,</hi> all <hi>ſweet content;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Even to <hi>Admiration, Aſtoniſhment.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At <hi>difference</hi> of the <hi>times,</hi> You live to ſee,</l>
               <l>How ſad you were, now joyfull may you be.</l>
               <l>Let all true <hi>Subjects</hi> yeild to God the praiſe;</l>
               <l>That did prolong Your Life, with happy Dayes.</l>
               <l>Behold the Place once you were in ſorrow;</l>
               <l>Some time, to reſt your felf, you did borrow</l>
               <l>Your <hi>ſacred Majeſty</hi> made choyce then to reſt,</l>
               <l>With one of your faithfull <hi>Subjects,</hi> lov'd <hi>you</hi> beſt</l>
               <l>Mr. <hi>Francis Windham,</hi> of a happy Name;</l>
               <l>May he e're live in honour, and in Fame;</l>
               <l>His heart, and houſe, rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to entertain,</l>
               <l>So Gracious a Gueſt, with him to remain.</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:60904:18"/>
               <l>A Gueſt above all others, did excell;</l>
               <l>Who wiſht, with you for ever for to dwell.</l>
               <l>The times then were wilde, dangerous, and wood:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Windham</hi> adveutu'rd's Life, to do you good;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Francis, Free</hi> his Name doth ſignifie;</l>
               <l>Receiving you, his Name did dignifie.</l>
               <l>Behold the Place, that ſheltred my Dear Lord:</l>
               <l>(Who alwayes truſted in Gods holy Word)</l>
               <l>Which his Faithfull Servant did him afford,</l>
               <l>In time of need, and horrid Danger deep;</l>
               <l>When many for your Perſon then did weep;</l>
               <l>Your Grace kept waking, whiles that they did ſleep.</l>
               <l>Let's praiſe God, who did your Soul deliver,</l>
               <l>From cruel Men, and bloody <hi>Oliver.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your Gracious heart was ſad when you paſs'd by:</l>
               <l>And ſaw an Object of <hi>Englands Tragedy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Brave, Noble, Learned <hi>Digby</hi>'s Famous Seat:</l>
               <l>A Place of ſtrength, and beauty, moſt compleat.</l>
               <l>I ſhould but Eclipſe his great noble worth;</l>
               <l>Weakly, and lame, t'expreſſe it, and ſet forth.</l>
               <l>There is a Famous River, called <hi>Trent;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where thirty Rivers are into it ſent.</l>
               <l>Theſe ſeveral Rivers fall into her Flood:</l>
               <l>And thirty ſorts of Fiſh, to do men good.</l>
               <l>More various are the Favours of my King:</l>
               <l>Innumerable Comforts they do bring,</l>
               <l>From the greateſt Subject, unto the leaſt:</l>
               <l>Happy is he that hath ſo Rare a Gueſt.</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60904:18"/>
               <l>No thing is wanting, that may ſet forth</l>
               <l>Some part of Luſtre, of the Owners worth.</l>
               <l>A <hi>Windham</hi> brave, vert'ous, wiſe, did you cheriſh:</l>
               <l>This <hi>Windham</hi> kept you, that you might not periſh.</l>
               <l>The King of heaven highly him reward;</l>
               <l>That of my Soveraign had ſuch due regard.</l>
               <l>I ne're was in the Houſe of this brave Wight;</l>
               <l>And therefore know not fully how to write.</l>
               <l>Pardon (dear Prince) my weakneſſe, and accept</l>
               <l>A Mite, inſtead of Pounds, for my great Debt.</l>
               <l>During my Life, I will, Sir, dayly pray;</l>
               <l>God preſerve my <hi>Soveraign</hi> both Night and Day.</l>
               <l>When Crowns and honours ſhall be laid in Duſt,</l>
               <l>May <hi>Your</hi> Soule live, in <hi>Happineſſe,</hi> 'mongſt the Juſt.</l>
               <l>When Death ſhall put a Period to your Daies:</l>
               <l>God crown <hi>your ſoule,</hi> with wreaths of <hi>heav'nly baies.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:60904:19"/>
            <head>On <hi>his moſt excellent Majeſty, King</hi> CHARLESH. <hi>his exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted coming to the
Right honourable JOHN</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>his</hi> Houſe, <hi>at</hi> Henton S.
<hi>George.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WElcome <hi>dread Soveraign,</hi> welcome to this Place:</l>
               <l>Unto a <hi>Noble Lord,</hi> who loves <hi>your Grace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Royal Father</hi> here took great Delight:</l>
               <l>Pleaſing his <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nces,</hi> and his Eye moſt bright.</l>
               <l>Nought is here wanting, that may give content:</l>
               <l>Even to admiration, Raviſhment:</l>
               <l>For wholeſome Dwelling, and ſweet <hi>healthy Aire;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Few Places, in the County can compare:</l>
               <l>A neat compacted Houſe, in brave order;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rich Pictures, Hangings,</hi> and <hi>ſtately Border;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Land skips,</hi> and <hi>Maps,</hi> for to delight the ſence:</l>
               <l>With many other things, of <hi>Excellence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rich Curtains,</hi> and <hi>ſumptuous Tapestry:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rare and <hi>ſoft Beds</hi> of <hi>Down,</hi> whereon to <hi>lye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Walks, Water works, Gardens, Parks,</hi> Oh <hi>brave Seat!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where's nothing wanting to make it compleat:</l>
               <l>With other, <hi>ſumptuous, ſtately, coſtly</hi> things;</l>
               <l>Fit, well-becomeing the <hi>high ſtate</hi> of Kings.</l>
               <l>Nothing is wanting here, that may ſet forth,</l>
               <l>Some part of <hi>luſtre,</hi> of the <hi>Owners worth.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wellcome <hi>Emperial Monarch,</hi> I do ſay;</l>
               <l>Where You do come, you'l make a Halcyon Day.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shine</hi> forth <hi>bright Sol,</hi> unto my <hi>Soveraign dear;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſhow thy ſelf, now that he doth appear,</l>
               <l>Within this pleaſant kind of <hi>Paradice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God bleſſe your <hi>Councellors,</hi> that <hi>give advice.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60904:19"/>
               <l>Part of that Noble Order, that attend;</l>
               <l>The dew of heaven, ſtill on them deſcend;</l>
               <l>And all the reſt, that do my King follow;</l>
               <l>Let time, and death, all your Enemies ſwallow;</l>
               <l>Let glorious Planets all then now rejoyce:</l>
               <l>And we your <hi>Subjects,</hi> for to hear your voice;</l>
               <l>And ſee your ſacred Perſon, at this time;</l>
               <l>Extend your Vertues, 'bove a Grand Divine.</l>
               <l>And eke, bleſt <hi>Phyſician,</hi> for to cure,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Kings Evil,</hi> which many do endure.</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> is willing to do good:</l>
               <l>What rare Ver ues flow from <hi>Kings Royal Blood!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Heavenly Motions do their mindes incline;</l>
               <l>To move to <hi>heavenly Raptures,</hi> moſt ſublime.</l>
               <l>Before, or after your rich, ſtately cheer;</l>
               <l>Your Majeſty may hunt, the fat, brave Deer;</l>
               <l>Walk in ſweet Gardens, for to take delight;</l>
               <l>View Objects rare, for to content your ſight.</l>
               <l>Recreate with bowling, or other ſport,</l>
               <l>To ſee your <hi>Perſon,</hi> many will reſort.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your Gracious Perſon</hi> doth Mens mindes content;</l>
               <l>To ſee with joy Gods bleſſed <hi>Vicege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercury doth point</hi> before or behind:</l>
               <l>To ſhew the various changes of the wind:</l>
               <l>And on each ſide, he doth not then omit,</l>
               <l>To point to the place, that's proper, and fit,</l>
               <l>For to direct, where Boreas blaſts do blow.</l>
               <l>And to informe the Standers by, to know,</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:60904:20"/>
               <l>Nothing in this frail Life is firm and ſure:</l>
               <l>God grant us his Grace, for e're to endure.</l>
               <l>This Place your <hi>Royal Court,</hi> is fit to feaſt;</l>
               <l>So <hi>divine, rich, rare, ſumptuous</hi> a <hi>Gueſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shine forth, and ſhow your Rayes of <hi>Majeſty;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God bleſſe your Perſon, and Poſterity;</l>
               <l>That ſhall hereafter, I do hope ſucceed:</l>
               <l>From royal, gracious, King <hi>Charles</hi> loyns proceed.</l>
               <l>The Birds do now ſweetly melodious ſing:</l>
               <l>To welcome hither our moſt gracious King.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henton</hi> St. <hi>George</hi> is a mark of honour:</l>
               <l>That brave Progenitors caſt upon her.</l>
               <l>St. <hi>George</hi> is a high, noble mark of Fame:</l>
               <l>Kings, and Nobles will preſerve that great Name.</l>
               <l>The higheſt Order of our brave Nation:</l>
               <l>Which other famous Kings keep in faſhion,</l>
               <l>The Heavens do ſmile, and the fields look gay:</l>
               <l>For here is now kept high St. <hi>George</hi>'s Day.</l>
               <l>As much as tongue can ſpeak, and <hi>pen</hi> expreſſe;</l>
               <l>I'le wiſh, pray for, my Soveraigns happineſſe.</l>
               <l>I will expreſſe my love with heart and hand;</l>
               <l>And be, for ever, at your bleſt command.</l>
               <l>I will ſet forth my love with tongue, and pen;</l>
               <l>God ſave my <hi>King;</hi> let all Men ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>After your Progreſſes on Earth are paſt;</l>
               <l>God give you <hi>heaven,</hi> to raign in at laſt.</l>
               <l>There to be crowned an Eternal <hi>King;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For to praiſe God, and <hi>heavenly Anthems</hi> ſing.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60904:20"/>
            <head>Accroſticks <hi>Upon the</hi> Royall, <hi>and</hi> moſt Illuſtrious DUKE, IAMES STVART,
His Majeſties <hi>only</hi> Brother.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>JAMES,</hi> only <hi>Brother</hi> to our <hi>Gracious KING:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Abundant <hi>comforts,</hi> by your ſervice bring.</l>
               <l>Majectick <hi>Actions</hi> do your Name advance:</l>
               <l>England of late was in a diſmal Trance:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sweet Bleſsings</hi> hath, by our <hi>Sov'raigns good chance.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Strength of Gods arme, his Power you defend:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Life of Grace</hi> here live, unto the end.</l>
               <l>Up at laſt <hi>bleſt Soul</hi> mount, to <hi>Heavens</hi> Glory:</l>
               <l>A HOMER's <hi>Pen</hi> ſhall <hi>write</hi> your bleſſed <hi>Story.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, Vertue, Valour, and true Fame:</l>
               <l>Theſe do, in part proclaim your Royall Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:60904:21"/>
            <lg>
               <l>In time of Sorrow you did bare your part:</l>
               <l>Again regain'd your Honour, by Deſert.</l>
               <l>Majeſtie doth ſmile on your grand Merit:</l>
               <l>Ended this Life, Glory then inherit;</l>
               <l>Sing praiſes to God, by his ſacred Spirit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soar up aloft to <hi>heav'n,</hi> by Raptures high:</l>
               <l>Truth ſtill maintain, and its pure Dignity.</l>
               <l>Up, above the Clouds your Soul ſoar's aloft:</l>
               <l>Advancing towards Chriſt, your Soul he bought.</l>
               <l>Renown <hi>your name,</hi> brave <hi>Duke,</hi> by your rare deeds:</l>
               <l>'Tis from your Vertuous Actions it proceeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iames,</hi> that learned, wiſe, and Religious King;</l>
               <l>Admir'd amongſt all Nations, peace did bring.</l>
               <l>Magnificent Prince, that late rul'd this Land;</l>
               <l>Eternal Bleſſings wrought by his fair hand;</l>
               <l>Still let's admire him, for his grand Command.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir, you're a Royall Branch of that learn'd Sire;</l>
               <l>Truth did maintain, with Zeal as hot as fire.</l>
               <l>Unitie, Peace, and Love he did maintain;</l>
               <l>Amongſt his greateſt Enemies peace did gain.</l>
               <l>Rare, famous Duke, may you his Acts embrace;</l>
               <l>Truths Friends cheriſh, Enemies deface.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60904:21"/>
            <head>On <hi>the</hi> moſt Illuſtrious, <hi>and</hi> Religious Eliſabeth; DUTCHESSE of
<hi>YORK.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Bleſſed <hi>Peace of the Lord:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Loving ever to obey <hi>Gods</hi> pure <hi>Word.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In Life, and Death, God guide you by his Grace,</l>
               <l>Zealous of his glory: you ſhall ſee his Face.</l>
               <l>Angells at laſt convey your Soul to bleſs.</l>
               <l>Bright radiant Glory, <hi>heavens happineſs:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Even as Glaſſe doth run, <hi>and ſand paſſe away;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>greatest Beauty, one day turns to clay.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Heav'ns happy Harbour will receive your Soul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Satiate with Gods preſence, ne're condole.</l>
               <l>Ther's nothing that ſhall trouble you above:</l>
               <l>Up raiſed 'bove the World, by perfect love.</l>
               <l>A mind you have, to do thoſe things are good:</l>
               <l>Rich by your Faith, in <hi>Chriſt his precious blood.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There is no <hi>fear,</hi> where this is underſtood.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:60904:22"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Dukes, Kings, and Princes; one Day all muſt die:</l>
               <l>Unto their God aſcend, and mount on high.</l>
               <l>Treaſure immortal the good ſhall enjoy:</l>
               <l>Chriſt will tree them from this vain worlds annoy.</l>
               <l>Heaven is the happy Place where Saints do dwell:</l>
               <l>Each being content, not ſtriving to Excell.</l>
               <l>Sufficient Glory every Saint hath there;</l>
               <l>Singing <hi>praiſes</hi> to their <hi>Saviour</hi> dear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of <hi>heavens glory</hi> each <hi>Saint</hi> hath his part;</l>
               <l>Farr tranſcending the thoughts of humane heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Your bleſſed Saviour did your <hi>Soul</hi> Redeem;</l>
               <l>Ordain'd you happy, and of high Eſteem.</l>
               <l>Raign rare <hi>Dutcheſſe,</hi> a Queen in that fair Land;</l>
               <l>Kings are joyfull there to bear leaſt command,</l>
               <l>E're guided by the wile, Almighties hand.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60904:22"/>
            <head>On his Excellency <hi>George Monck,</hi> Duke <hi>of Albemarle.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Duke, God give you <hi>length of dayes</hi> on <hi>earth:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>E're make you happy both in <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>death.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our Gracious King you happ'ly dia reſtore:</l>
               <l>Riches immortal may you have therefore.</l>
               <l>God grant, hereafter you may ſee Gods face;</l>
               <l>Enthron'd by Chriſt unto a heavenly Place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Majeſtie doth on you moſt ſweetly ſhine,</l>
               <l>Oh, may Gods Providence you ſafely keep,</l>
               <l>Noon, Day, and Night, whether you wake, or ſleep.</l>
               <l>Chriſt, and <hi>King Charles</hi> your Soul and Body love;</l>
               <l>King, and Subject your faithfull Love approve.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60904:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>George</hi> is the <hi>Name</hi> of fair brave <hi>Englands Saint:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> made <hi>happy,</hi> by your noble <hi>hand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our <hi>Gracious Soveraign</hi> will hear our complaint;</l>
               <l>Religiouſly rule, and govern this <hi>Land.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Great God of Heaven and Earth you ever bleſſe;</l>
               <l>Ev'n here on <hi>earth,</hi> with <hi>heav'nly happineſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Maj'ſtick <hi>Monck,</hi> Mirrour of this <hi>Nation:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh what brave order, and ſtately Faſhion;</l>
               <l>Now that our Gracious King doth rule and raign:</l>
               <l>Chriſt grant him <hi>Nestor</hi>'s years, here to remain.</l>
               <l>Kings to exceed, yea great King <hi>Charlemain.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>God gave you Life; and in his full <hi>due time,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Exalted you, unto a Place ſublime;</l>
               <l>Oh may Gods <hi>Bleſsing</hi> ſtill on you deſcend:</l>
               <l>Remaining to our King, a faithfull Friend.</l>
               <l>God hath rewarded you, for your great pains;</l>
               <l>Eternal Manſions be your bleſt Souls gains.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Geometry</hi> cannot <hi>meaſure</hi> your great worth;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Emanent Logicks</hi> Science not ſet forth;</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Arithmat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cks</hi> uſefull Art number.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rhetorick</hi> cannot more <hi>divinely</hi> move;</l>
               <l>Gracious <hi>Moncks</hi> heart, his Soveraign for to love;</l>
               <l>Exceeding the kind, faithfull Tuttle Dove.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:60904:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſick,</hi> for ſweetneſs d'ont exceed your voyce,</l>
               <l>Of making ſo good, praiſe worthy a choyce</l>
               <l>Not Nature, but three Nations for't rejoyce.</l>
               <l>Chriſt <hi>bleſſe</hi> you, and the ſacred Trinity<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>King Charles</hi> to bring, to's <hi>Royall Dignity.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grand famous Warrier, maiſt thou ſtill win fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Eternize your great vertues, and your Name</l>
               <l>Oh let all <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> of our <hi>joyes</hi> pertake;</l>
               <l>Rouze other Nations, and their Valour wake.</l>
               <l>Great God of <hi>heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> and Earth, <hi>our Champion bleſs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n with all joy, Eternall happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Riches, and Honours ſhall paſſe away</l>
               <l>Ended this life, enjoy a glorious Day,</l>
               <l>Oh that my <hi>Dull Muſe</hi> could <hi>fully</hi> expreſſe,</l>
               <l>Rich, rare, tranſcendent, <hi>future happineſſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God</hi> hath in <hi>heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n,</hi> I hope, laid up for thee,</l>
               <l>E're <hi>bleſſed Manſion</hi> to Eternitie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mount up aloſt you ſhall to <hi>Saints</hi> above.</l>
               <l>On Angells wings your <hi>bleſſed Soul</hi> ſhall fly,</l>
               <l>Neere to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> mounting up on high,</l>
               <l>Convey'd by <hi>Angels</hi> to a place ſublime:</l>
               <l>Kings, <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>Martyrs:</hi> there may your ſoul ſhine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60904:24"/>
            <head>On <hi>the moſt</hi> Reverend FATHER <hi>in</hi> GOD; William Juxon, Arch-<hi>bishop</hi>
of <hi>Ganterbury,</hi> His <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>Willing ever to ſerve your <hi>Soveraign Lord;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Induſtrious to advance Gods <hi>ſacred Word.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laud ſtill the Lord, that did our Soveraign bring,</l>
               <l>In his due time unto his Fathers Throne:</l>
               <l>Advance the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Jah,</hi> of God alone.</l>
               <l>May you ſhine bright, like a Tranſcendent one.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jeſus</hi> the grand true <hi>Biſhop</hi> of your <hi>Soul,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Up hath rais'd you, by your <hi>Soveraign</hi> dear,</l>
               <l>Xalted on high, in our Hemiſphear.</l>
               <l>On your Royal Maſter you did fix your love:</l>
               <l>None higher then your ſelf did he approve.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:60904:24"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When he was to ſuffer that fatal ſtroake</l>
               <l>It made your heart to bleed yea heart of Oake:</l>
               <l>Lamenting ſore, for your <hi>Soveraigns</hi> death,</l>
               <l>Like to have coſt you your dear vitall breath.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> you did put all your truſt:</l>
               <l>Angells ſtill guide you, till you turn to duſt:</l>
               <l>Mongſt <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angells</hi> ſhine among the <hi>Juſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jn Troublous Times, at laſt you liv'd to ſee</l>
               <l>Unto your joy, his <hi>ſacred Majeſty;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Xonerated from his pain and grief:</l>
               <l>Our gracious God did ſend him his relief.</l>
               <l>Next to <hi>Gods</hi> Name, let us extoll him chief.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wayting long, at laſt our Sunn did ariſe:</l>
               <l>In radiant manner, clearing our dim eyes;</l>
               <l>Lamenting him, whoſe Death they did deplore.</l>
               <l>It was a Bleſt Time, when brave <hi>Monck</hi> did bring,</l>
               <l>Again our <hi>gracious Soveraign,</hi> Lord, and King;</l>
               <l>May we due praiſes of our <hi>Soveraign</hi> ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jt pleas'd our good God, after many years;</l>
               <l>Unto your joy, being almoſt drown'd in tears;</l>
               <l>Xalt your griev'd heart, and ſorrowfull minde,</l>
               <l>On your <hi>Dread Soveraign Lord,</hi> who was ſo <hi>kinde,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now double joy doth ſpring: your <hi>King</hi> to find.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60904:25"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When that ſable Day, and ſad Night of Death,</l>
               <l>Iudicious <hi>Juxon,</hi> ſtop thy <hi>Soveraigns</hi> breath:</l>
               <l>Lord, what a time was then to your ſad Soul:</l>
               <l>Lamenting his departure, did condole:</l>
               <l>In grief, and tears, you were almoſt drown'd then.</l>
               <l>A better, happy time, God hath you ſent:</l>
               <l>May <hi>heav'ns King crown you,</hi> with moſt <hi>ſweet content.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jn <hi>heavenly</hi> things you do ſpend your <hi>Dayes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unto your <hi>grand King,</hi> and <hi>Creators</hi> praiſe.</l>
               <l>Xhorting <hi>Chriſtians</hi> purely for to live;</l>
               <l>Oh bleſſed <hi>Soul,</hi> ſuch fair Inſtructions give;</l>
               <l>None, <hi>none</hi> but <hi>Chriſt,</hi> can our <hi>foul ſinnes</hi> forgive.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wiſdome advanceth Men of good deſert;</l>
               <l>It crown's that <hi>Man,</hi> who hath a <hi>perfect heart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord</hi> inflame your heart with <hi>holy fire;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let your Affection be of like deſire.</l>
               <l>In place, as your <hi>Grace</hi> is advanced high;</l>
               <l>Angels after <hi>Death,</hi> with <hi>your ſoul</hi> then flie;</l>
               <l>Mount up aloft to higheſt <hi>Majeſtie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Jnſtall'd a <hi>Biſhop</hi> in a <hi>bleſſed time;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Uprai's'd to honour, to a place ſublime;</l>
               <l>Xalted may you be to place of Bleſſe;</l>
               <l>Of heavenly Glory, and Happineſſe,</l>
               <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in <hi>Robes of Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:60904:25"/>
            <head>On <hi>the moſt</hi> Reverend FATHER <hi>in</hi> GOD <hi>Edward,</hi> LORD BISHOP
<hi>of</hi> NORWICH.</head>
            <head type="sub">My ever Honoured Priend and Kinſman.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Chriſt called you unto his <note n="*" place="margin">Dean of Chriſt Church in Oxen.</note>
Church again</l>
               <l>Enabling you in's ſervice to take pain.</l>
               <l>But long you did not then continue there</l>
               <l>But in a higher Place did ſoon appear.</l>
               <l>You reap'd a happy Guerdon for your love;</l>
               <l>Both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> did your wayes approve.</l>
               <l>God guided you by his ſacred <hi>Spirit:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>After this Life, <hi>Eternall joyes inherit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You preacht before the <hi>Commons,</hi> and our <hi>King:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Praiſing the Lord, that did our Soveraign bring,</l>
               <l>At laſt, with joy, unto his Fathers Throne:</l>
               <l>It was the glorious work of God alone.</l>
               <l>Your loyalty unto our Gracious Lord,</l>
               <l>Doth now unto you great comforts afford.</l>
               <l>Your healing precious Balm was well apply'd:</l>
               <l>The king the happy Bridegroom to our Bride.</l>
               <l>The bride, this Kingdome was married at laſt:</l>
               <l>Your Griefs, and Sorrows then were everpaſt.</l>
               <l>Oh let us, to our God, moſt handfull be.</l>
               <l>That did preſerve his Royall Majeſtie.</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60904:26"/>
               <l>Oh how I did rejoyce to read you <note n="†" place="margin">Sermons before the King and
Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Books</l>
               <l>And therein ſee <hi>your gracious heart</hi> and <hi>looks</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It did m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drooping ſpirits then revive,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God garde</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Sov'raign, keep him</hi> long <hi>alive</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Enemies <hi>he</hi> may overcome:</l>
               <l>Preſerve his Ofspring till the Day of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me.</l>
               <l>Let REYNOLDS then ever renowned be:</l>
               <l>For's healing Balme, for Royal Sov'raignty.</l>
               <l>He did prepare the Phyſick, for to cure,</l>
               <l>The Maladie which long we did indure.</l>
               <l>God bleſſe all the happy Phyſicians skill.</l>
               <l>That did obey Gods word, and it fulfill.</l>
               <l>The happy Patriots of our Country dear,</l>
               <l>Which doth our Gracious Soveraign love and fear.</l>
               <l>Unite their hearts in Bonds of faithfull Love;</l>
               <l>Loving's Majeſtie, and his Acts approve.</l>
               <l>And being made happie with all ſweet content,</l>
               <l>By a brave, bleſſed, healing Parliament.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60904:26"/>
            <head>On my Ever Honoured Friend and Kinſman Doctor <hi>Iohn Caſtle</hi> Eſquire, one of the
Clerks of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Privy Seale.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Iohn Gratious your name doth ſignify:</l>
               <l>Oh! how good Names, the owners Dignify</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hereditus</hi> was for brave <hi>Hiſtory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nathan</hi> a Prophet, in Divine <hi>Miſtery.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Caſting Your Care on God, hath ſet You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Advanc'd you to former Dignitie.</l>
               <l>Still by your Vertues, get to honours ſeate,</l>
               <l>The grand King of Kings make you ſtill Compleat,</l>
               <l>Laid low by Warre, yet Chriſt hath raiſ'd you up.</l>
               <l>Even to Dine, and at laſt with him to Sup.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ieſus of Nazareth, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you in your Wayes:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his praiſe</l>
               <l>H <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> high of <hi>Bleſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Can you Wiſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:60904:27"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Conſtant e're, in ſerving your Lord, and God:</l>
               <l>And alwaies diligent, to hear his word.</l>
               <l>Serving your Lord, and Maſter faithfully,</l>
               <l>The King, of Heav'n, and Earth you dignifie</l>
               <l>Laud God above: who hath Preſerv'd your life:</l>
               <l>E're made you happy, for a ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uous wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In all your troubles, you were not diſmaid:</l>
               <l>On God, you put your tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: were not afraid.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hoſanna</hi> then at laſt, may you: ſoul ſing:</l>
               <l>None could you draw, from your dear Soveraign (King)</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave your mind reſt, after ſo much pain;</l>
               <l>Advanc't you to Honour, and place Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</l>
               <l>Still did you w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te, upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and of God:</l>
               <l>The Tyrants pow'r's removd, his cruel Rod.</l>
               <l>Lord thou haſt brought my friend; for to ſit down,</l>
               <l>Ev'n under the Rayes, of a bleſſed Crown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Iudicious Sir, I love your learned Arts:</l>
               <l>On vertue grounded, and Renowned parts.</l>
               <l>Heavenly fire, doth inflame your mind;</l>
               <l>Nought can remain of Dro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, b'ing thus refind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> make you happie: both in Life, and Death,</l>
               <l>Advance his glory, with your vital breath;</l>
               <l>Standing ſtill firm, and conſtant in your faith:</l>
               <l>Truth to maintain, and what our Saviour ſaith.</l>
               <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uding the Lord, in the moſt ſadeſt time,</l>
               <l>Even then your ſoul, did mount to place ſublime.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60904:27"/>
            <lg>
               <l>In contemplation, and divineſt things:</l>
               <l>On things Celeſtial, and the King of Kings;</l>
               <l>High Heav'nly Raptures, for to place your minde:</l>
               <l>None ſo ſweet, and good on Earth, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> to find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Clouds of calamity, being paſt away,</l>
               <l>Advanc't you now to ſee, a Halcyon day.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salvator Mundi,</hi> doth you comfort give,</l>
               <l>The Lord grant your bleſt ſoul, long life to live.</l>
               <l>Lord when thy ſervants work, is done and paſt:</l>
               <l>Eternal joyes, give his bleſt ſoul, at laſt</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This have I poorly drawn, from your good Name</l>
               <l>Let Bleſſed Angels, blow your Trump of Fame.</l>
               <l>You have been like a Father unto me,</l>
               <l>God bleſs your ſoul, to all Eternity.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:60904:28"/>
            <head>On <hi>the</hi> right worſhipful, <hi>and noble minded</hi> Gentleman, <hi>Henry Ford,</hi>
Eſquire; <hi>one of his</hi> Majeſties <hi>JUSTICES</hi> of the Peace, <hi>in the</hi> County
<hi>of</hi> Devon, <hi>and</hi> Lieutenant Colonel to the Honorable Sir <hi>JOHNDRAKE,</hi> Knight,
<hi>and</hi> Barronet, &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>High, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v'nly knowledge doth inrich thy mind;</l>
               <l>Eternal happineſs may your Soul find:</l>
               <l>Not Nature, but Grace, doth thy Saviour pleaſe:</l>
               <l>Reſtor'd by Chriſt, cur'd of ſinns diſeaſe;</l>
               <l>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n brightneſs of his Glory maiſt thou ſhine:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Far more Tranſcendent than a brave Divine.</l>
               <l>Ore Topps and Mountains thy Wit doth aſpire:</l>
               <l>Rais'd up to Heav'n By a heavenly fire;</l>
               <l>Death ſhall not quench the flame of thy deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>High doſt thou mount by thy rich Phantaſie:</l>
               <l>Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h can't turn it into an Extaſie.</l>
               <l>None none but Chriſt, did that brave Martyr ſay:</l>
               <l>Raiſe up thy though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; live with Chriſt for aye,</l>
               <l>Yet, happy to have all things here on Earth:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Far more happy to have a bleſſed death.</l>
               <l>On things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thy bleſt Soul doth not feed;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Divine; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of immortal ſeed;</l>
               <l>Death wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> come, thou fear'ſt not, oh bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v'nly breed.</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60904:28"/>
               <l>Wiſdom and Learning doth adorn a man,</l>
               <l>I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes him flouriſh, and things duly ſcan:</l>
               <l>Learning adorns a worthy noble mind:</l>
               <l>Learning invites men to beloving, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind:</l>
               <l>It doth inrich the mind with knowledge ſtore:</l>
               <l>Adds luſtre to its witt, and makes it more:</l>
               <l>Magnifie Gods great Name; praiſe him therefore.</l>
               <l>Could I your worthy noble parts rehearſe:</l>
               <l>And write the ſame in high immortal verſe:</l>
               <l>I ſhould then to your Country; then declare;</l>
               <l>Your Vertues and your Learning rich and rare.</l>
               <l>A mirrour to the World thou doſt appear,</l>
               <l>Thy Learning and thy Iudgment ſhineth clear:</l>
               <l>Go on bleſt Saint in thy brave way to bliſs,</l>
               <l>And at the laſt enjoy Heav'ns happineſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lieutenant <hi>Ford,</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One of thoſe famous Worthies of my King:</l>
               <l>God in his due time to happineſs bring:</l>
               <l>Eternal happineſs after thy death:</l>
               <l>To Gods glory, er'e ſpend your vital breath.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:60904:29"/>
            <head>On the Worſhipfull, Francis Poulet, Eſquire; <hi>One of his</hi> Majeſties
<hi>JUSTICES</hi> of the Peace, <hi>for the</hi> County <hi>of</hi> SOMERSET.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Fair may your Name be writ in book of Life:</l>
               <l>Rais'd is your Soul'bove Earth, and mortal ſtrife.</l>
               <l>Angells attend you both in life and death:</l>
               <l>Nature b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſpent, yield up your vital breath.</l>
               <l>Chriſt will call home your Soul in his due time,</l>
               <l>Into his Manſſion; where it bright ſhall ſhine;</l>
               <l>Sweet Saviour, grant it ſo, in place ſublime.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pondering and muſing on Divine things:</l>
               <l>On bleſſed Angells, and the King of Kings.</l>
               <l>Up may your Soul riſe 'bove Earthly Story,</l>
               <l>Lord mount it up to Eternal Glory.</l>
               <l>Ended this life, may your Soul mount on high,</l>
               <l>There to reem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in to all Eternity.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:60904:29"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Famous, and Renow'd; were your bleſt Anceſtors</l>
               <l>Records of 'time, ſhew forth your Progenitors.</l>
               <l>A famous Author doth preſerve their Name:</l>
               <l>Not to be mention'd, but with Trump of Fame.</l>
               <l>Chriſt hath obtain'd, by his precious merit,</l>
               <l>In Heav'n a place, your Soul to inherit;</l>
               <l>Solace with Saints, and the Holy Spirit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Prudent in your actions, and circumſpect;</l>
               <l>Oh may Gods mercy on you ſtill reflect.</l>
               <l>Up may you riſe unto a Heav'nly Throne;</l>
               <l>Lauding your bleſſed Saviour, God alo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>E'r may you on Earth; and heaven happy be;</l>
               <l>Tranſcendent live to's Sacred Majeſtie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>FRANCIS,</hi> Free, <hi>your</hi> Name <hi>doth ſignifie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Right</hi> good Name <hi>doth the</hi> Owner <hi>digniſie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And may the</hi> holie Spirit <hi>you</hi> comfort <hi>give;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nurtur'd on</hi> Earth, <hi>in</hi> Heaven <hi>for to live.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caſting your</hi> care <hi>on</hi> God, <hi>and</hi> him <hi>to</hi> ſerve.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In</hi> health <hi>and</hi> ſickneſſe, <hi>till</hi> grim Death <hi>ſhall
come.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sweetly</hi> reſting <hi>in</hi> hope, <hi>till</hi> Day <hi>of</hi> Dome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pleaſures immortal may you e're enjoy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>On</hi> earth, <hi>and</hi> heav'n, <hi>paſt this</hi> vain Worlds <hi>annoy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Up may your</hi> ſoul <hi>mount, to</hi> eternal bleſs;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord give you</hi> true, <hi>and</hi> perfect happineſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re may you ſhine, like</hi> ſtarr, <hi>celeſtial</hi> bright;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T'enjoy the</hi> comforts <hi>of</hi> tranſcendent Light.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60904:30"/>
            <head>On Coming to the Right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>COVRTNEY</hi> POLE, Knight and Barronet, his
Court Holden at <hi>Brod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winſor</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> the Fourth day of
<hi>Aprill</hi> 1661. to take the Oath of <hi>Alegiance.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVElcome to Brave Sir <hi>Courtney Pole</hi> his Court:</l>
               <l>Where many <hi>Loyall Subjects</hi> do reſort.</l>
               <l>Come Sware With joy to be true to your <hi>King:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It was the hand of God that did him bring,</l>
               <l>Into his <hi>Native Land</hi> to <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Raigne:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Rejoyce now Loving Friends, with might and maine,</l>
               <l>That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing doth ſway the ſepter of this Land:</l>
               <l>Oh! be true and Faithfull, to his Command.</l>
               <l>Do you what good, true <hi>Subjects</hi> doth befit:</l>
               <l>That you may hereafter downe in <hi>Heav'n</hi> ſit;</l>
               <l>With Faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his bleſt traine:</l>
               <l>With <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angles</hi> there for to remayne.</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60904:30"/>
               <l>The Clouds of blackneſſe, Now are paſt away</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Soveraigne Lord:</hi> hath brought a Glorious Day.</l>
               <l>Let then your Loyal hearts: with true Love burne:</l>
               <l>After you're ſworne you may againe returne:</l>
               <l>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o your Houſes: or Places Where you Dwell,</l>
               <l>Wiſhing and praying, none More may rebell.</l>
               <l>Living in peace and L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving Each other:</l>
               <l>Doing good, not hurt to your Deare brother.</l>
               <l>Let Writh and Anger ceaſe, that God may bleſſe:</l>
               <l>And ſend you Everlaſting Happineſſe.</l>
               <l>May'th the King, and's People live and ſo accord,</l>
               <l>Truly to love and ſerve our gratious Lord.</l>
               <l>May the King and's People live and agree,</l>
               <l>In true Love, Peace, and perfect Amitie</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:60904:31"/>
            <head>On hearing <hi>of his</hi> honoured, <hi>and</hi> reverend Kinſman, Edward Reynolds, Doctor
in <hi>Divinity,</hi> conſecrated Lord <hi>BISHOP</hi> of <hi>NORWICH.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>As God hath call'd you to a Biſhops Seat,</l>
               <l>Long may you live, and preach Gods Word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat.</l>
               <l>May your holy life give ſuch example;</l>
               <l>That your Charge o're Sin and Vice may trample:</l>
               <l>May your holy life ſuch example give,</l>
               <l>That may proclaim, that Chriſt in you do live;</l>
               <l>And by his power doth foul Sin deſtroy:</l>
               <l>And ſo at laſt enter your Maſters Joy.</l>
               <l>Welcome dear Kinſman, to <hi>Norwich</hi> City,</l>
               <l>A place rare, ancient, famous, and pretty,</l>
               <l>By your heavenly Doctrine you mount aloft;</l>
               <l>And ſhow how Chriſt mans ſinful ſoul hath bought.</l>
               <l>The preciouſneſs of Faith you do deſcrie:</l>
               <l>And mount the Soul up to Eternitie:</l>
               <l>To ſee the face of Chriſt through holy Faith;</l>
               <l>To behold his Word, what our Saviour ſaith.</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60904:31"/>
               <l>Repentance alſo you declare to men:</l>
               <l>God bleſs your heav'nly Tongue, and golden Pen</l>
               <l>And all your parts of Body, Soul, beſide;</l>
               <l>That you may o're a heav'nly Flock ſtill guide:</l>
               <l>To Heav'nly <hi>Cannan,</hi> that Coeleſtial Hill,</l>
               <l>Comfort the Saints with heav'nly <hi>Manna</hi> ſtill.</l>
               <l>God long continue your moſt happy dayes;</l>
               <l>To tune your Tongue, to your Creators praiſe:</l>
               <l>Inſpire your heart with a heav'nly flame;</l>
               <l>As long as life continue praiſe his name.</l>
               <l>Accept my language from a faultring Pen,</l>
               <l>Who will reverence you 'mongſt worthi'ſt men.</l>
               <l>Oh happy then, when holy Saints doth greet;</l>
               <l>May we at leſt our bleſſed Saviour meet,</l>
               <l>And go with him into eternal bliſs,</l>
               <l>To have a Manſion with thoſe Saints of his.</l>
               <l>When your work is ended, and parted hence,</l>
               <l>God give your Soul a happy recompence.</l>
               <l>When that your days, on Earth are paſt and done,</l>
               <l>God make you happy to behold his Son.</l>
               <l>When that your days on Earth ſhall paſs away,</l>
               <l>God grant your ſoul a Divine Halcion day.</l>
               <l>For thoſe famous learn'd books you <hi>do</hi> indite,</l>
               <l>May God your Name in's book of Life down write.</l>
               <l>When Death ſhall ſhut, and cloſe up your bleſt eyes</l>
               <l>May your Soul with Angels mount 'bove the Skies.</l>
               <l>Where Saints, Holy Martyrs, all that are Bleſt:</l>
               <l>There may your Bleſſed Soul, for ever reſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:60904:32"/>
            <head>ON Reading of ſome part of the Church HISTORY Of BRITAIN: Writen By the learned Pen of that
Famous Hiſtorian. <hi>THOMAS F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LLERD. D.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom time of Pagan Britains, laſt of Kings,</l>
               <l>That rul'd, and Raign'd, in this Famous Iſle;</l>
               <l>Thou do'ſt in ample manner, ſo place things:</l>
               <l>By thy melifuous, and moſt learned ſtile.</l>
               <l>From birth of Jeſus Chriſt, our moſt dear Lord:</l>
               <l>Thou do'ſt begin thy ſacred Hiſtory,</l>
               <l>Concluding Truth, out of his Holy word,</l>
               <l>And do'ſt unfold, many hiden miſtery.</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:60904:32"/>
               <l>The Church of <hi>Britain,</hi> thou do'ſt ſo ſet forth,</l>
               <l>Advance its Glory, and make it ſhine bright;</l>
               <l>That After-Ages may behold thy worth,</l>
               <l>And ſee its ſplender, in the Darkſome night.</l>
               <l>How many learned Books, haſt thou turnd o're?</l>
               <l>Extract the quintiſence, of Ancient times:</l>
               <l>And taught the world; what they knew not before,</l>
               <l>Enriching their minds, with thy Precious lines.</l>
               <l>Grand Mirrour of this Nation to Advance,</l>
               <l>Your worth and Fame, there wants a Homers Pen:</l>
               <l>For to ſet forth, things Paralel to men,</l>
               <l>Of Higheſt learning, and of greateſt Fame,</l>
               <l>For to Preſerve Thy Rich: and famous Name.</l>
               <l>Whiles <hi>Britain's</hi> Iſle doth flouriſh, and wax green,</l>
               <l>Thy Famous works with wonder ſhall be ſeen,</l>
               <l>And be Renown'd unto After-Ages:</l>
               <l>In your well writ, Admir'd, and learned Pages.</l>
               <l>The Ancient <hi>Britiſh</hi> Church thou do'ſt revive:</l>
               <l>Advance, Coroberate: and keep alive.</l>
               <l>Old Father-Time, Thou do'ſt confer with all:</l>
               <l>Materials for thy Building; great, and ſmal,</l>
               <l>Out of many Studies, in this land:</l>
               <l>Thou haſt made ſearch, with thy learned hand.</l>
               <l>The Famous <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſle, Thou 'aſt ſurrounded:</l>
               <l>Both Truth and falſhood, You'ave deeply ſounded:</l>
               <l>Whiles that Great <hi>Britain,</hi> bears that famous Name:</l>
               <l>Your learned works ſhall ſtil preſerve thy Fame:</l>
               <l>Let others write, in whatſoever ſtile:</l>
               <l>Thy writings ſhall be Mirrour, in this Iſle;</l>
               <l>Spred far, and travel into other lands:</l>
               <l>Be Admir'd, that come from your curteous hands.</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:60904:33"/>
               <l>Your famous Books, ſhall preſerve your Name:</l>
               <l>And Angels high reſound your Trump of Fame.</l>
               <l>The Famous Worthies of After Ages:</l>
               <l>Shall admire your Golden learned Pages.</l>
               <l>As long as God by time ſhall leave a man;</l>
               <l>All ſorts of men your Books ſhall love to ſcan.</l>
               <l>When life's ended; and Death ſhall cloſe your eyes:</l>
               <l>Your Body Imortal to Glory, ſhall Ariſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60904:33"/>
            <head>ACCROSTICKS ON The HONOURABLE and truly NOBLE S<hi rend="sup">IR</hi> WIL. MORICE K<hi rend="sup">T</hi>. One of the SECRETARIES
OF STATE Unto His moſt EXCELLENT MAJESTY, K. CHARLES II.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHiles that you ponder on the Kings Affairs,</l>
               <l>Judicious Sir, for to advance the State;</l>
               <l>Lab'ring diligently, early and late:</l>
               <l>Lord guide your faithful heart to ſerve our King,</l>
               <l>In Gods due time let Angels your ſoul bring;</l>
               <l>Aſcending up, and then with Angels fly:</l>
               <l>Mount up aloft unto the Hea'vns high.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:60904:34"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Majeſtick <hi>Morice,</hi> with your Golden Pen,</l>
               <l>Of your great Actions, and Affairs of Men,</l>
               <l>Rich, rarer Pen then mine, I want to write,</l>
               <l>Royal great things, not mean ones to indite.</l>
               <l>In Jeſus Chriſt, you do put all your Truſt:</l>
               <l>Chriſt crown your ſoul with Kings amongſt the juſt,</l>
               <l>E're you attain it, you muſt turn to duſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wiſedom and Learning doth advance a man,</l>
               <l>It makes him prudent; and things duly skan,</l>
               <l>Learning adorns a worthy noble mind:</l>
               <l>Learning invites men to be curteous kind;</l>
               <l>It doth enrich the mind with knowledge ſtore.</l>
               <l>Adds luſtre to his parts, and makes them more,</l>
               <l>Magnifie Gods great Name, <hi>praiſe him therefore.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>More care and pains no Creature can fulfill;</l>
               <l>Oh! you do help both King and Subject ſtill,</l>
               <l>Raiſing your heart up to that ſacred hill.</l>
               <l>Jeſus ſtill make you happy all your days:</l>
               <l>Changes and chances doth not trouble thee,</l>
               <l>E're in your mind b'ing noble, loyal free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wit, wealth and learning cannot keep from death,</l>
               <l>In dying poſture we yield up our breath.</l>
               <l>Labour of mind and body being paſt,</l>
               <l>Laid low in grave, we muſt be all at laſt.</l>
               <l>In and by Jeſus Chriſt, our Saviour dear,</l>
               <l>Ariſe you ſhall out of your grave of duſt,</l>
               <l>Mounting aloft to live among the juſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:60904:34"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Melifuouſe in your words and actions ſtill:</l>
               <l>Oh! how I <hi>love,</hi> and honour pens mans skill,</l>
               <l>Reſplendent <hi>raptures</hi> high doth enrich your mind,</l>
               <l>Juſt royal King <hi>Charles</hi> doth you great <hi>buſineſs</hi> find.</l>
               <l>Chriſt ſtill direct you, and be e're your guard,</l>
               <l>Eternal <hi>Bleſsings</hi> be your bleſt <hi>Reward.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whiles that ingenious fancies ſtir the brain,</l>
               <l>It makes ſome things appear, but light and vain:</l>
               <l>Lord ſo advance your <hi>Wit,</hi> your <hi>Wealth,</hi> and <hi>State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Living and dying <hi>make you fortunate</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>your bleſsed Saviour dear.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Awake, though dead before him, ſhall appear.</l>
               <l>Mount up on high, and <hi>Heav'nly Anthems hear.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mercy and Truth adorn your <hi>gracious ſp'rit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>On <hi>ſublime things</hi> to think on, and to write.</l>
               <l>Robes of <hi>Chriſts righteouſneſs</hi> may you put on,</l>
               <l>In and by him, <hi>that is that holy one:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Chang'd one day you ſhall be, yet need not fear;</l>
               <l>Enthron'd at laſt <hi>by Chriſt your Saviour dear.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>BE pleas'd to <hi>reliſh</hi> well what I impart,</l>
               <l>I love <hi>my Soveraign</hi> with my <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It is in your power <hi>to make me live.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh! could I to you <hi>Fairer Preſent</hi> give,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>mean bare words</hi> of a <hi>Countrey Hue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not <hi>Court</hi>-like, <hi>Sublime,</hi> which are <hi>fit for you.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Judicious <hi>Morice,</hi> you do move in <hi>Sphear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Near and about my <hi>Grand Soveraign dear;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:60904:35"/>
               <l>Your <hi>word</hi> to Him may make me <hi>happy</hi> then:</l>
               <l>You ſhall command my <hi>Body, Heart</hi> and <hi>Pen.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Th' <hi>Operation</hi> of my head b'ing old:</l>
               <l>My Wit is dul, my brain of temper cold.</l>
               <l>If it were hot and ſtrong, ſhould be for you,</l>
               <l>The higheſt fruit of <hi>brain</hi> is but your due.</l>
               <l>I fear with tedious lines for to offend,</l>
               <l>I will therefore conclude, and make an end.</l>
               <l>I will, I ſay, end my <hi>earthly ſtory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Praying God may crown you with <hi>immortal glory.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60904:35"/>
            <head>ON THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL, VALIANT, AND TRULY NOBLE MINDED GENT. S<hi rend="sup">IR</hi> JOH. CLOBERY
Knight.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>JUſtice and Goodneſs doth your heart affect;</l>
               <l>On ſacred works you do no time neglect:</l>
               <l>Heavenly thoughts your mind doth pitch upon,</l>
               <l>None, none but Chriſt, I there let it fix on.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Chriſt hath advanc'd you by his word and ſword,</l>
               <l>Laud and praiſe ſtill your bleſſed heav'nly Lord.</l>
               <l>Oh! may your actions ever happy be,</l>
               <l>Bleſſed for ever to Eternity</l>
               <l>Everlaſting Lord your ſoul ever bleſs.</l>
               <l>Raiſe up your heart and mind to happineſs</l>
               <l>Yn and by Jeſus Chriſt his righteouſneſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:60904:36"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ingenuous Sir, I love your valiant Arts,</l>
               <l>On <hi>Vertue</hi> grounded, and <hi>renowned parts.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Heavenly fire doth inflame your <hi>brave mind:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nought can remain of <hi>duſt,</hi> b'ing thus <hi>refin'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cares and great troubles doth attend the <hi>Saints;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lord hear my honour'd friend, <hi>his juſt complaints,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Open the gates of Heav'n, and entrance make</l>
               <l>By <hi>fervent prayer,</hi> for thy Saviours ſake.</l>
               <l>E're thou wert born, thou wert ordain'd to dye:</l>
               <l>Raiſe up your heart to 's heav'nly Majeſty;</l>
               <l>Y In height of bleſs, up with <hi>bright Angels</hi> fly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Joy after ſorrow, <hi>you enjoy at laſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh render thanks, <hi>now griefs are over paſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Heav'n made you happy by a gracious King,</l>
               <l>N New praiſes to your <hi>Maker</hi> daily ſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Chriſt at laſt give your ſoul eternal gain,</l>
               <l>Labour being paſt, and all <hi>Earthly pain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh Lord make you happy in life and death.</l>
               <l>Be careful in ſpending your <hi>vital breath.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ever in praiſe and honour of Gods name,</l>
               <l>Raiſed by Chriſt to place of happineſs,</l>
               <l>Ynveſted be in's Robes of Righ eouſneſs.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:60904:36"/>
            <head>ON THE HONOURABLE COLONEL, AND MY EVER HONOURED FRIEND S<hi rend="sup">IR</hi> JOHN DRAKE Knight and Baronet,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>RIght noble Knight I do admire your wit,</l>
               <l>In acting of high <hi>matters,</hi> proper, fit.</l>
               <l>Your Love was ever conſtant to the Crown,</l>
               <l>Which hath purchas'd you <hi>great and high renown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your Name ſhall ever flouriſh and wax green,</l>
               <l>And 'mongſt the <hi>Worthies</hi> of this age be ſeen.</l>
               <l>Your Wiſdom ſolid is, moves in due place,</l>
               <l>It advanceth your name, and noble race. <note n="(*)" place="margin">Of Knights and
Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Who can in <hi>England</hi> exceed <hi>Drakes</hi> great Name?</l>
               <l>His worthy Anceſtors of noble Fame.</l>
               <l>Thou didſt out-ſtrip the Kings En'mies: Pleaſe him ſtill,</l>
               <l>And to his Laws obedient and to his will.</l>
               <l>His preſence did revive your loyal heart,</l>
               <l>His abſence did increaſe your greater ſmart.</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:60904:37"/>
               <l>The <hi>Crommelites</hi> from him could get no Bayes,</l>
               <l>It was to the King he did owe his praiſe.</l>
               <l>He would not yield to any Tyrant great;</l>
               <l>In his actions he walk'd upright, compleat.</l>
               <l>Oh what a high and lofty brain he had!</l>
               <l>Not to buckle, with Ruler was ſo bad.</l>
               <l>Who durſt to ſit in's <hi>Royal Soverains Throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which did belong to our King <hi>Charles</hi> alone.</l>
               <l>He could not therefore love him in his heart,</l>
               <l>For ſhooting at King <hi>Charles</hi> his <hi>mortal dart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He was the man, King <hi>Charles</hi> his blood did ſhed;</l>
               <l>He was accurſed both alive and dead,</l>
               <l>For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntting off King <hi>Charles</hi>'s ſacred head.</l>
               <l>Oh, how he did ſuck that moſt precious blood,</l>
               <l>Who to three Nations would have done much good.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Drake's</hi> fit to be Counſelor to a King:</l>
               <l>He ever ready was comforts to bring.</l>
               <l>His Wit's profound, his Genius mounts up high.</l>
               <l>He ſerves his royal Maſter faithfully.</l>
               <l>I muſt conclude, Gods Spirit did you guide,</l>
               <l>That in your acting did not walk aſide.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60904:37"/>
            <head>AN ELEGIE ON THE Death of that moſt Excellent, Religious and unparralel'd Queen of BOHEMIA,
Only Daughter to <hi>JAMES</hi> KING OF GREAT <hi>BRITAIN,</hi> SISTER TO <hi>CHARLES</hi> THE
FIRST, AND WIFE to the moſt Illuſtrious ELECTOR, <hi>FREDERICK</hi> KING OF
<hi>BOHEMIA.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>A Brave ſtately Cedar's faln in this land;</l>
               <l>There's no withſtanding of th' Almighties hand.</l>
               <l>Ah cruel death, why didſt thou now appear?</l>
               <l>To rob us of a Jewel rich and rare.</l>
               <l>The Mirrour of this Iſſe is now deceaſt,</l>
               <l>Her death hath many Mourners now increaſt.</l>
               <l>My gracious King and Nobles they do mourn,</l>
               <l>And faithful ſervants o're her ſacred Urn</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60904:38"/>
               <l>They mourn in heart, with black Cloaks to the ground,</l>
               <l>For ſuch a Queen on earth's ſcarſe to be found.</l>
               <l>This vertuous Queen of fair <hi>Bohemian</hi> land,</l>
               <l>who in the true faith did moſt firmly ſtand</l>
               <l>Of all the famous Nations far and near,</l>
               <l>Her like and parralel doth not appear.</l>
               <l>She was extracted from a Royal ſtock;</l>
               <l>Death came too ſoon, and at her door did knock.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>James</hi> that great King of Peace, and learned skill,</l>
               <l>Death would not ſpare for all his learned quill:</l>
               <l>Nor yet his vertuous daughter ſhining bright,</l>
               <l>But muſt away with him in ſable night.</l>
               <l>Great Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> not more vertuous rare,</l>
               <l>Then this great Queen within our Hemiſphear.</l>
               <l>When death doth ſummon, we muſt all away,</l>
               <l>From Princely furniture, to beds of clay.</l>
               <l>Before Queen <hi>Anne,</hi> that famous Queen ſhe dy'd,</l>
               <l>There was before a glorious ſtar eſpy'd.</l>
               <l>'Twas of wonder and admiration:</l>
               <l>'Tis ſad to yield account of its ſtation.</l>
               <l>Many ſad things it did portend i'th'end,</l>
               <l>Which God Almighty then did quickly ſend:</l>
               <l>Great Wars and Blood-ſhed then did after come,</l>
               <l>Which rang'd o're many parts of Chriſtendome:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Germany</hi> did feel the ſtroke moſt great,</l>
               <l>A heavy Famine little for to eat.</l>
               <l>King <hi>James</hi> that learned and renowned King,</l>
               <l>Which to this Kingdom did great Bleſſings bring</l>
               <l>Of Peace and Happineſs to this Nation,</l>
               <l>Both Penty, Riches, and ſtately faſhion.</l>
               <l>God hath Crown'd our Nation with great content,</l>
               <l>A gracious King, and bleſſed Parliament.</l>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60904:38"/>
               <l>King <hi>James</hi> did write of that ſtrange <hi>blazing ſtar;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Seen before Queens <hi>Anns</hi> death, that Princeſs rare</l>
               <l>'Twas to invite this <hi>Gueſt</hi> God <hi>ſent this ſtar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe friends and neareſt kin <hi>good Princeſs</hi> are:</l>
               <l>Who though <hi>they run the race of men, and dye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Death ſerves <hi>but to refine their Majesty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So did my Queen from hence her <hi>Court remove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>put on death,</hi> to be <hi>enthron'd above:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then ſhe's not dead,</hi> but <hi>ſleeps,</hi> no good <hi>Prince</hi> dyes,</l>
               <l>But like the <hi>Days-Sun, only ſets to riſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since her ſad death, <hi>a bright ſtar did appear:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I hope our <hi>Royal Queen</hi> will ſoon land here,</l>
               <l>And will arrive at this <hi>famous City,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With <hi>noble Lords, ſweet Ladies,</hi> and <hi>pretty.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cleopatria</hi> not equal to thee,</l>
               <l>Though fil'd with <hi>riches,</hi> perfect <hi>Majeſty,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Attended with a ſumptuous <hi>ſtately Train,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet was at laſt by poyſonous <hi>Aſp</hi> there ſlain.</l>
               <l>This bleſſed Queen was by death ſummon'd hence,</l>
               <l>Rais'd up to Heav'n to receive recompence.</l>
               <l>The <hi>bleſſed Angels</hi> did her ſoul convay,</l>
               <l>Freed from all Troubles, and the worlds annoy.</l>
               <l>At laſt to enter her grand Maſters joy,</l>
               <l>Her many choice vertues for to recount,</l>
               <l>Would up into afair Great volumn mount,</l>
               <l>I want a <hi>Homer</hi> or a <hi>Mayhews</hi> pen,</l>
               <l>Her worth and vertues to declare to men.</l>
               <l>Her faith and patience was of that brave fame,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall preſerve her great and famous name:</l>
               <l>Some famous Poet ſhall adorn your Herſe,</l>
               <l>And make you live by his immortal verſe.</l>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:60904:39"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Du Bartus,</hi> heav'nly Poets fit to write</l>
               <l>Of your rare Vertues which did ſhine moſt bright.</l>
               <l>Beams of Eternal light lighten your ſoul,</l>
               <l>Rich, rare, tranſcendent without mans controle.</l>
               <l>I wiſh your ſoul high perfect happineſs</l>
               <l>Amongſt bleſt Saints with everlaſting bleſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tranſcendant hrppineſs</hi> I hope you find,</l>
               <l>None but Jeſus Chriſt fil'd your heart and mind.</l>
               <l>None but <hi>Anne</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> like to thee,</l>
               <l>In <hi>radiant vertues,</hi> and high Majeſty.</l>
               <l>Moſt bleſſed Queen you did prepare for death,</l>
               <l>Advanc'd towards heav'n, part with vital breath.</l>
               <l>Nature moſt kind, and grace you did ſet forth,</l>
               <l>Ever to ſhew your vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and great worth.</l>
               <l>Bright ſhining vertues did your ſoul adorn,</l>
               <l>Robes of Chriſts righteouſneſs you have put on,</l>
               <l>In and by Jeſus Chriſt moſt happy be,</l>
               <l>Aſcend with Angels to the <hi>Trinity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No earthly thing doth ſatiate the heart.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The holy Spirit</hi> doth all grace impart.</l>
               <l>Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd vertuous <hi>Queen</hi> your ways were firm and good,</l>
               <l>Advanc'd by Chriſt, your Saviours precious blood.</l>
               <l>Night of death came, thou didſt go to be's bride,</l>
               <l>Ere to ſit down by Chriſt your Saviours ſide.</l>
               <l>Bounty and Gods free love to you <hi>blest Saint</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Raiſ'd you up, God heard your juſt complaint.</l>
               <l>In full ripe years you were now cal'd away;</l>
               <l>Advanc'd by Chriſt, with your bleſt Bridegroom ſtay.</l>
               <l>Chriſt call'd you hence unto his Fold;</l>
               <l>Our Saviour calls both Young and Old:</l>
               <l>No Riches, Honour, Youth can ſtay,</l>
               <l>Strong ſturdy Death takes all away.</l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60904:39"/>
               <l>The Baly of our bleſſed Lord,</l>
               <l>Away muſt go, obey his word.</l>
               <l>No longer time he will neglect,</l>
               <l>Chriſts calls away his bleſt elect</l>
               <l>Brought now at laſt unto your home.</l>
               <l>Riches to have, not of earth's lome.</l>
               <l>Indeed that Portion will endure,</l>
               <l>Gods mercies are for ever ſure:</l>
               <l>Away ſhe went, when Chriſt did call,</l>
               <l>No dallying death will take all.</l>
               <l>The greateſt, richeſt, and the ſmall:</l>
               <l>Brought low by death unto her grave,</l>
               <l>Robes of Chriſts righteouſneſs to have.</l>
               <l>In Jeſus Chriſt the put her truſt,</l>
               <l>And is now gone unto the juſt.</l>
               <l>Nothing ſo dear that ſhe did love,</l>
               <l>Treaſures immortal did approve.</l>
               <l>Chang'd is your body, and refin'd ſhall be;</l>
               <l>Call'd to the preſence of the Trinity.</l>
               <l>Night of death come, with Angels ſhe did fly</l>
               <l>Saints to live with to all Eternity.</l>
               <l>Chriſt hath remov'd you to a greater joy,</l>
               <l>Earths comforts, unto heavens, but a toy.</l>
               <l>In earthly things there's but lintle pleaſure,</l>
               <l>Above the skie is immortal treaſure.</l>
               <l>Chriſt ranſom'd your ſoul with his precious blood,</l>
               <l>Only that Balm can do our ſouls moſt good,</l>
               <l>Near Jeſus Chriſt, I hope your ſoul doth reſt,</l>
               <l>Sav'd by your Saviour, lives amongſt the bleſt.</l>
               <l>The ſoul is wearied by its travels here,</l>
               <l>Away ſhes gone unto her Saviour dear,</l>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:60904:40"/>
               <l>Her glaſs being run, her ſoul is fled away</l>
               <l>With her Redeemer ever for to ſtay.</l>
               <l>What can I think, ſpeak, or write more then?</l>
               <l>She doth deſerve! ſhall have a better Pen.</l>
               <l>To write of her high Vertues, glorious Name,</l>
               <l>Which learned Authors ſhall recount her Fame.</l>
               <l>Chriſt is your bleſſed Spouſe, your Birdegroom, All,</l>
               <l>Your God, your Saviour, King Emperial.</l>
               <l>He hath advanc'd you to eternal bliſs,</l>
               <l>Let's be as careful not to do amiſs.</l>
               <l>She was a mother unto Princeſs ſtore,</l>
               <l>God bleſs them here on earth, and evermore.</l>
               <l>Their ſeverel names I cannot recount;</l>
               <l>Some are on earth, others to heav'n did mount.</l>
               <l>Prince <hi>Robert</hi> is a ſtout couragious wight,</l>
               <l>And hath put many enemies to flight:</l>
               <l>God bleſs his Highneſs long here on the earth,</l>
               <l>And make him truly happy at his death.</l>
               <l>Grieve not immoderately, brave Prince, her ſon,</l>
               <l>For your dear mother that is dead and gone</l>
               <l>From earth to heav, n, that bleſſed place of reſt,</l>
               <l>To live with glorious Saints for ever bleſt.</l>
               <l>Wherefore then ſhould I ſay, that ſhe's dead;</l>
               <l>Whenas ſhe's gone, where life it ſelf is bred.</l>
               <l>Then mourn no more but ſet your heart at reſt,</l>
               <l>You ſhall be like her carcaſe in the cheſt:</l>
               <l>As num, as wan, as pale and cold as ſhe,</l>
               <l>Pray God your lives and deaths no worſe may be.</l>
               <l>Grieve then no more, put not your mind to pain,</l>
               <l>For her pure ſoul in heaven doth remain.</l>
               <l>He that writes more, more time of grief muſt borrow,</l>
               <l>Let him then bring his wit, I'le bring my ſorrow.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:60904:40"/>
            <head>ACCROSTICKS On her moſt ſacred MAIESTY.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Elizabeth bleſſed peace of the Lord,</l>
               <l>Loving his Saints, and his ſacred word.</l>
               <l>In Jeſus Chriſt you did put all your truſt,</l>
               <l>Zealous for Religion, lives amongſt the juſt.</l>
               <l>A bleſſed change you lived for to ſee,</l>
               <l>Bleſſed be God, his ſacred Majeſty:</l>
               <l>Enthron'd compleat in his dear Fathers <hi>Throne;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The praiſes chiefly belongs to God alone;</l>
               <l>Hoſanna let us ſing to that holy One.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Queen 'bove all Queens in glory bright,</l>
               <l>Up mounted high unto that heav'nly light.</l>
               <l>Eternal Joyes now to be partaker,</l>
               <l>Ever to praiſe with Saints your Creator;</l>
               <l>Now ſinging Anthemes to your bleſſed Maker.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of all the bleſſings of a righteous ſoul,</l>
               <l>Freedom from ſin, and this vile worlds controle.</l>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:60904:41"/>
               <l>By death of Chriſt you have obtain'd life,</l>
               <l>Overcome the world, and all mortal ſtrief.</l>
               <l>Hallalujahs ſing in his height of bleſs,</l>
               <l>Ever partaking of heav'ns happineſs.</l>
               <l>Made now a member of that heav'nly hoſt;</l>
               <l>In praiſing Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</l>
               <l>Angels convey'd your ſoul, that heavnly Poſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Away ſhe's gone unto that place of bleſs,</l>
               <l>Immortal Saints enjoy full happineſs:</l>
               <l>Adieu bleſt Queen, we mortals will prove juſt,</l>
               <l>Always eſteeming your moſt precious duſt,</l>
               <l>The grave hath your body, world your fame,</l>
               <l>Heaven your <hi>ſoul,</hi> your ſon preſerves your <hi>Name.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though <hi>you be gone,</hi> your fame is left behind.</l>
               <l>I hope your ſon will prove as gracious kind.</l>
               <l>My muſe is dull, my <hi>Taper</hi> gives dim light,</l>
               <l>Yet may invite ſome better <hi>Pens to write.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ile put an end to this my <hi>mortal ſtory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hoping God bath <hi>crown'd</hi> her with <hi>immortal glory.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60904:41"/>
            <head>On Hearing of the RIGHT WORSHIPFUL, <hi>JOHN MERREFIELD</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Made one of
the KINGS SERJEANTS AT LAW, Andin Election tobe a Judge.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHen our renowed King <hi>Charls</hi> came to his <hi>Court,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Many Lords and noble perſons did reſort,</l>
               <l>Who came to ſee'm, and <hi>kiſs his royal haud,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>B'ing come from far into his native land.</l>
               <l>All ſorts of men of our brave Engliſh Nation,</l>
               <l>Were glad in heart for their <hi>Kings reſtauration.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It was a time then freely for to give,</l>
               <l>To ſee their gracious King then for to live</l>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:60904:42"/>
               <l>In royal Honour, and in noble Fame,</l>
               <l>God long increaſe, and propagate his Name,</l>
               <l>It was a time to confer honours ſtore,</l>
               <l>The cauſe did well require long before.</l>
               <l>Brave <hi>Monck</hi> and <hi>Patriots</hi> did love our <hi>King,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who us'd their <hi>beſt means</hi> ſpeedily to bring</l>
               <l>Him to ſit and act with them in's Parliament,</l>
               <l>To make <hi>good Laws</hi> with one and <hi>joynt conſent.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As <hi>Guerdon</hi> of's love did the King impart</l>
               <l>Rewards of <hi>honour</hi> for their good deſert.</l>
               <l>Of thoſe brave Nobles and <hi>deſerving men,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'm far unworthy to recount by Pen:</l>
               <l>Yet may I not my <hi>honoured friend forget,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>former favours</hi> make me much <hi>in debt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let <hi>Merrefields</hi> name advance to his height,</l>
               <l>May Kings and Princes in him <hi>take delight.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>worthy Squire,</hi> ſurmount an <hi>noble Knight.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I heard that King <hi>Charles</hi> will make him a Judge:</l>
               <l>His domeanor is ſuch, no man will grudge,</l>
               <l>To hear of his good and high <hi>preferment,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which long continue till his <hi>interment.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Loyal learned <hi>Merrefields</hi> worth do ſhine</l>
               <l>In <hi>equal ſplendor</hi> to ſome <hi>rare Divine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I did long ſince conceive within my breſt,</l>
               <l>When that my <hi>Royal Soverain</hi> came to reſt,</l>
               <l>And to ſit down <hi>on his dear Fathers throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For to enjoy <hi>three kingdoms of his own:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That then his <hi>Majeſty</hi> would him advance,</l>
               <l>When being come from <hi>Holland,</hi> fertile <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Meer <hi>love</hi> and <hi>favour</hi> would my <hi>Sovraign</hi> move</l>
               <l>On honeſt <hi>Merrefield</hi> to fix his love.</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60904:42"/>
               <l>For <hi>Learning, Law, Loyalty,</hi> and the reſt.</l>
               <l>He doth deſerve mongſt Lawyers counted beſt.</l>
               <l>When he ſhall come to ſit in juſtice <hi>place,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lewd vitious men he will then diſgrace.</l>
               <l>Advance the vertuous, and the <hi>godly man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And of mens <hi>various actions</hi> duly ſcan.</l>
               <l>When he ſhall mount up to grand <hi>Juſtice ſeat,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His parts with <hi>luſtre,</hi> then will ſeem compleat.</l>
               <l>Immitate honeſt <hi>Crew, Hutton, Denham,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Doddrige Walters, Jenkins, Crook</hi> and <hi>Popham:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Both theſe and many learned Lawyers more:</l>
               <l>Their worth he'l practice, and yet keep in ſtore.</l>
               <l>My Pen is weak and lame for to ſet forth,</l>
               <l>His <hi>profound wiſdom,</hi> and his <hi>noble worth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Full fraught with <hi>favours</hi> of his <hi>Soveraign Lord,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Stil careful to preſerve <hi>Gods ſacred word.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>E're may you have <hi>your Kings love here on earth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>King of Kings</hi> make you happy in your death.</l>
               <l>May Gods <hi>Spirit</hi> joy you e're above all,</l>
               <l>Be ready when God for your ſoul ſhall call.</l>
               <l>As there are ſeveral degrees 'mongſt men,</l>
               <l>So in Heav'n, Saints, Angels and Syraphen.</l>
               <l>As the <hi>King hath honoured</hi> my dear friend,</l>
               <l>So to his Family let it extend.</l>
               <l>According to his worth let's praiſes yield</l>
               <l>Unto that well <hi>deſerving Merrefield.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>After all honour when't ſhall pleaſe your Maker,</l>
               <l>Of <hi>heavens joys</hi> may you be made <hi>partaker.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Enough you'l have when <hi>Angels</hi> ſhall you bring</l>
               <l>To glory your bleſt <hi>ſoul</hi> to Chriſt your King.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:60904:43"/>
            <head>ON HEARING OF THE DEATH Of my dear and admired SOVERAIGN LORD, KING CHARLES the
Firſt.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GRief doth afflict, and pierce my tender heart,</l>
               <l>That death hath ſlain my Soverain with his <hi>dart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cannibals they were, did act the devils part,</l>
               <l>Make brave <hi>royal</hi> Branches, and whole Kingdoms ſmart.</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60904:43"/>
               <l>Was there no <hi>mean</hi> to qualifie your <hi>ire?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But that your wrath muſt burn with <hi>helliſh fire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh <hi>curſed Monsters</hi> to do ſuch athing,</l>
               <l>To <hi>murder</hi> our <hi>Soveraign Lord</hi> and <hi>King.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſay, 'twas ſin that did provoke</l>
               <l>God for to ſtrike us with ſo <hi>ſharpe a stroke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For to deprive him of his <hi>precious breath,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſnatcht his life away by <hi>untimely death,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ah <hi>curſ'd Miſcr'ant</hi> to lay thy hand on <hi>him,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For to commit ſo horrid <hi>bloody ſin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did not thy heart with ſorrow then relent,</l>
               <l>And cauſe thy wicked heart for to <hi>repent?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſo great miſchief, <hi>bloody, crying ſin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That will eternal vengeance after bring.</l>
               <l>Where were thy eys within thy curſed head!</l>
               <l>To ſtrike the fonntain of Life, our Soverain dead:</l>
               <l>I wept, and bath'd mine eyes in morning tears,</l>
               <l>For death of my <hi>dear Soveraign</hi> Lord and <hi>King:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It was to qualifie my grief and fears:</l>
               <l>For that ſad Act, Repentance it will bring.</l>
               <l>Had I not been in my dear brothers houſe,</l>
               <l>I might been cut by <hi>Soldiers</hi> ſmals a mouſe: <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>l.
bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Cap in K. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>l.</hi> th. Firſt his Army, liv'd and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t
<hi>Waym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uth.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>They would ſoon have holpt me from my weeping,</l>
               <l>And brought me to an untimely ſleeping.</l>
               <l>God will revenge him on that curſed wretch.</l>
               <l>Who did his murdering hand out-boldy ſtretch</l>
               <l>For to cut off our gracious <hi>Sov'raigns</hi> head:</l>
               <l>The grief thereof did ſtrike me almoſt dead,</l>
               <l>That Monſter that did cut off that ſacred head,</l>
               <l>Did ſtrike the Nobles, and the kingdom dead.</l>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:60904:44"/>
               <l>Dead in Repute, in Miſery, and in fame,</l>
               <l>Stain to our noble Nation, Engliſh name.</l>
               <l>The wicked Vipers haſten'd him away,</l>
               <l>Gods holy Angels did his ſoul conveigh</l>
               <l>To heav'nly <hi>Canaan,</hi> there to be crown'd King,</l>
               <l>With glorious Saints and Angels Anthemes ſing.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60904:44"/>
            <head>On ſight of ſuppoſed ANGELS, In ſhape of DUCKS, Hovering over King <hi>Charles</hi>
the firſt, when he was beheaded,</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHy do you talk of <hi>Ducks?</hi> they <hi>Angels</hi> were!</l>
               <l>Souldiers could not diſcern them, their eyes</l>
               <l>The bright <hi>Angels</hi> waited for to conveigh [b'ing blear,</l>
               <l>King <hi>Charle's</hi> ſoul, though's life were made a prey.</l>
               <l>His <hi>blood</hi> did <hi>drown</hi> their Conſciences full deep,</l>
               <l>Whiles many for our Soveraign Lord did weep.</l>
               <l>The <hi>bleſſed Angels</hi> hover d'ore his head,</l>
               <l>And waited on him <hi>after he was dead:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who did conveigh <hi>his bleſsed ſoul</hi> to bliſs,</l>
               <l>To a heav'nly Manſion, endleſs happineſs,</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:60904:45"/>
            <head>ON Sight of the Death of that HONOURABLE &amp; LEARNED Kt. S<hi rend="sup">IR.</hi> HEN. HYDE On the fourth of
<hi>March</hi> 1650.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>RIch, rare, tranſcendent <hi>Hyde</hi> when thou didſt <hi>die,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My heart did grieve my eys did weep; the <hi>sky</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was overcaſt with ſable <hi>blackneſs</hi> ſad,</l>
               <l>For to behold an <hi>action was ſo bad.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Loyal brave <hi>Hyde</hi> when thou didſt looſe thy <hi>head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My <hi>heart with grief and inward ſorrow bled.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The fourth of <hi>March</hi> was that <hi>fatal day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That brave Sir <hi>Henry Hyde</hi> was ſnatcht away</l>
               <l>by cruel, ſudden and <hi>untimely death:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who in <hi>high language</hi> ſpent his vital breath.</l>
               <l>He faithfully ſerv'd his royal Maſter,</l>
               <l>His enemies made him of <hi>death a Taſter.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It griev'd me for to ſee his head fall down;</l>
               <l>He fell ſo low, <hi>for love unto the Crown.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:60904:45"/>
               <l>I hope brave <hi>Hyde</hi> did not the Merchants wrong,</l>
               <l>But that it was a <hi>laſh</hi> of a <hi>falſe tongue.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I could ſcarce write theſe <hi>lines</hi> without <hi>weeping eye.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My <hi>eyes</hi> did weep when that <hi>brave ſoul did die.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though's <hi>body</hi> dead, his ſoul ſhall e're remain</l>
               <l>With his Lord Chriſt for ever to reign.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry,</hi> Rich Lord, it doth import,</l>
               <l>E're lov'd the word, to it reſort.</l>
               <l>No man more loyal to his King,</l>
               <l>Rebellious men did his ſoul ſting,</l>
               <l>Yet's Prayers did in Gods ears ring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hyde</hi> laid down his life for ſerving his King</l>
               <l>In loyal manner, <hi>b'ing a bleſsed thing.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Death did not ſad him,</hi> nor his heart <hi>diſmay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Expecting to live <hi>with his Lord Chriſt alway.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His ſoul is gone <hi>to eternal reſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ended now is his <hi>mortal ſorrow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No piercing cares can him moleſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Everlaſting joyes did him follow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Repine not therefore <hi>at his bliſs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou live well, <hi>thy joy ſhall be like his.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hope doth aſſure me, <hi>Hyde's</hi> ſoul's gone to <hi>heav'n:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In this <hi>life,</hi> though of's life he were bereav'n.</l>
               <l>Death did deprive <hi>him here of a few days:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Enemies ſent him to <hi>heav'n</hi> his God to praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:60904:46"/>
            <head>On Sight and Hearing of my HONOURED FRIEND, <hi>GEORGE F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LFFORD,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
One of His Majeſties Juſtices of the PEACE For the County of DORSCET, at Prayers with his
Family, the tenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1661.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BY fervent Prayer thou doſt ſo diſcry,</l>
               <l>And raiſe the <hi>ſoul up to Eternity.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mount up <hi>rich ſoul</hi> with your <hi>heart and voice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And cauſe thoſe hear you, <hi>in their hearts rejoyce.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God long continue <hi>your moſt happy days,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To tune <hi>your tongue to your Creators praiſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Inſpire your heart <hi>with a heavenly flame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As long as life continue, <hi>praiſe his name.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60904:46"/>
               <l>Aſſiſt you in <hi>your Prayers by his ſpirit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>After <hi>may your ſoul heav'n inherit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Accept my language from a <hi>faultring pen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who will reverence you'mongſt <hi>worthy men.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May your prayers aſcend and pierce the sky,</l>
               <l>And your ſoul <hi>mount</hi> up, and with <hi>Angels</hi> fly.</l>
               <l>After you've done your ſervice, parted hence,</l>
               <l>God give your <hi>ſoul in heav'n a recompence.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When that your <hi>days on earth are paſt away,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God give your ſoul a <hi>divine alchion day.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſts</hi> precious <hi>blood</hi>'s your balm, that <hi>balms</hi> your bleſs.</l>
               <l>God bring your ſoul to <hi>endleſs happineſs.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By Chriſts his merits <hi>ſo rewarded be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Make you happy to all <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:60904:47"/>
            <head type="sub">ON MY HONOURED FRIEND, <hi>GEORGE F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LFFORD,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> at Prayers
with his Family, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>BY zealous Prayer thou doſt ſoar aloft,</l>
               <l>Fly up by Faith to Chriſt our ſouls who bought.</l>
               <l>Dear 'twas indeed, it coſt him his heart blood,</l>
               <l>To ſave our <hi>precious ſouls,</hi> and do men good.</l>
               <l>Oh what a various <hi>change</hi> of <hi>divine things,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Flows from your <hi>bleſt mouth</hi> to the King of Kings,</l>
               <l>Your heav'nly tongue doth inchant the ear</l>
               <l>With raviſhing comforts of our Saviour dear.</l>
               <l>What heav'nly language doth from you flow,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nectar</hi> proceeds from you, though here below.</l>
               <l>A conſtant ſervant to our <hi>Soveraign</hi> true,</l>
               <l>With honour you are graced, 'tis your due.</l>
               <l>Your Graces are divine and eminent.</l>
               <l>Tranſlucent ſhine, rich, rare and tranſcendent.</l>
               <l>Oh my dear friend you do my mind content,</l>
               <l>To admiration, divine raviſhment.</l>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:60904:47"/>
               <l>Moſt rare you do pray for our gracious King:</l>
               <l>The King of Kings your ſoul to glory bring</l>
               <l>In his due ſeaſon to a glorious ſtate,</l>
               <l>To live and reign with the regenerate.</l>
               <l>O what ſweet Raptures doth proceed from thee,</l>
               <l>Raviſh the mind with divine Extaſie,</l>
               <l>Until my ſoul ſhall up to Heav'n aſcend,</l>
               <l>God make me happy with ſo good a friend.</l>
               <l>Who can conduct my ſoul to heavenly bliſs,</l>
               <l>To full fruition of heav'ns happineſs.</l>
               <l>Ah bleſſed ſoul what more then can I ſay,</l>
               <l>Night of death come, may you ſee a glorious day.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60904:48"/>
            <head>ON S<hi rend="sup">IR.</hi> ROB. BRET Wearing a LEEK IN HIS HAT ON S. Davids Day, And in playing Gleek with
two Noble Ladies.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FRom Royal <hi>Tuders</hi> ſtock <hi>Eliza</hi> came,</l>
               <l>That famous and renowned Queen, whoſe fame</l>
               <l>Shall ever live in fair great <hi>Britains</hi> Iſle,</l>
               <l>Her gracious Actions ſtill doth on us ſmile:</l>
               <l>Her name doth fragrant ſmell amongſt the Saints,</l>
               <l>Our gracious King will hear our juſt complaints.</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:60904:48"/>
               <l>This day being <hi>Davids</hi> Saint doth me invite,</l>
               <l>To ſhew forth a beam of its radiant light,</l>
               <l>A King and Prophet that did bravely raign</l>
               <l>Beyond the State of that great <hi>Charlamayn.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A man very rare after <hi>Gods own heart,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Oh may we in Gods ſervice bear a part.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza</hi> that Majeſtick Royal Queen,</l>
               <l>Her Leek on <hi>Davids</hi> Day was to be ſeen,</l>
               <l>Which ſhe did wear in honour of that day</l>
               <l>In ſilk and ſilver beautiful and gay,</l>
               <l>Though firſt of <hi>March</hi> ſeem'd in the moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The valiant old <hi>Britains</hi> ſtrong and ſtout,</l>
               <l>Foild their enemies, and gave them the rout.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Leek</hi> did wear and for a ſign diſplay,</l>
               <l>Vanquiſht their enemies, made them run away.</l>
               <l>It is a joy to ſee the old green Leek</l>
               <l>Worn in friends Hats, and ſee them now at <hi>Gleek.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe noble Ladies doth become the place,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heroick</hi>-like, playes with a comly grace.</l>
               <l>Friends, long may you wear Leeks, and at Gleek play,</l>
               <l>And when you marry Sir, be an <hi>Alchion</hi> Day.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:60904:49"/>
            <head>ON D<hi rend="sup">R.</hi> T. FULLERS Putting down the NORMAN RACE, in his Hiſtory of the Church of
<hi>Britain.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>SEt up again that Royal <hi>Norman Race,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which you of late turn'd down with ſuch diſgrace.</l>
               <l>But you are wiſe to run the race of men,</l>
               <l>To change your mind as you can change your Pen.</l>
               <l>Is this your noble zeal to Royal Stock,</l>
               <l>To turn them down, as of it make a mock!</l>
               <l>Turn't up again, and do no longer ſtay,</l>
               <l>Leſt being ſpide, it carries gain away,</l>
               <l>For writing of that goodly ſtately book,</l>
               <l>If that our Soveraiu Lord ſhould on it look;</l>
               <l>Peruſe that irkſome paſſage, and it find,</l>
               <l>It would no doubt be much againſt his mind:</l>
               <l>You did it then 'gainſt your mind and reaſon:</l>
               <l>To ſet it up, 't would be connted treaſon.</l>
               <l>But that time is paſt, now a better's come.</l>
               <l>Arnend that Act leſt you receive your dome.</l>
               <l>Now that the learned Doctors life's ended,</l>
               <l>Some friend of his may get it to be mended.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:60904:49"/>
            <head>ACCROSTICKS, ON THO. FULLER Doctor of Divinity, and late Prebend of New SARUM.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THy Name is botomleſs, ſo is your Art:</l>
               <l>High skil'd in Hiſtory: for to Impart.</l>
               <l>Open your Treaſury, and let men view:</l>
               <l>Mines moſt profound of Riches, old, and new,</l>
               <l>Aſcend Rare Sir, unto that Radiant skie:</l>
               <l>Soare up aloft unto the Heavens high.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60904:50"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Fair Charecters of Grace may your heart hold,</l>
               <l>Vertues ſacred, pure, and more worth then Gold.</l>
               <l>Lifting up your heart, to your Saviour Dear:</l>
               <l>Low be in ſelf, high in your Hemiſphear.</l>
               <l>E're may you be Bleſt, by Gods Heav'nly Grace:</l>
               <l>Raiſ'd up at laſt; to ſee His glorious Face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thrones mighty high, ſhall be ſubdu'd at laſt:</l>
               <l>Heav'n continues, when Earthly things are paſt.</l>
               <l>Oh! then Remember Sir, your later end:</l>
               <l>Mercy, and Peace obtain to be your friend.</l>
               <l>As all things paſs, on this vain Globe below,</l>
               <l>Soar up aloft, where better fruits doth grow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fervent in your Prayers, and in Preaching,</l>
               <l>Unto Heav'n, you do direct your Teaching.</l>
               <l>Lay hold on Chriſt, let him be your ſure Guide:</l>
               <l>Lay hold on Him, and you ſhall never ſlide.</l>
               <l>E're that the World was made, he did Elect,</l>
               <l>Ranſom'd his Servants, and will them Protect.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tranſcendent, in your Calling, manifold,</l>
               <l>High Raptures to Declare, out of Gods word.</l>
               <l>Open your mouth wide, and ſet forth his Praiſe:</l>
               <l>Mongſt bleſſed Saints, may you ſpend all your Dayes.</l>
               <l>After this mortal life, is gone and paſt:</l>
               <l>Soare up to Heav'n, and live with Chriſt at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fair, ſacred Beames, that doth your Soul Inſpire:</l>
               <l>Up raiſe your Heart, and ſo Inflame deſire.</l>
               <l>Like to a Conduit-pipe, thou do'ſt convay,</l>
               <l>Laborious ſweetneſs, and Chriſts Rich Aray.</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60904:50"/>
               <l>E'rlaſting Joyes, prepared for you in ſtore:</l>
               <l>Remain for your Bleſt Soul, for evermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tranſlucent <hi>Fuller,</hi> with thy Golden Pen,</l>
               <l>High Miſteries utter, and declare to Men.</l>
               <l>Old and young, both ſexes, give Dainty food:</l>
               <l>Meat ſeaſonable, choice: new, old, and good.</l>
               <l>As Fountain-like: flow out with ſtreams of Grace:</l>
               <l>Saciate enough the Saints, in every Place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Full to the Brim, let thy ſweet Nectar flow:</l>
               <l>Up to the Higheſt Heav'ns, let your thoughts go.</l>
               <l>Laid low in ſelf, moſt high, thy Soul will mount:</l>
               <l>Lord let his Rich Soul, be of High account.</l>
               <l>Eternal God, Crown him, in his laſt Dayes;</l>
               <l>Record his Name, for Ever Thee to Praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60904:51"/>
            <head>ON The hearing of the general Muſter of the Honorable COLONEL, S<hi rend="sup">IR</hi>. Iohn Drake. Knight,
<hi>and</hi> Baronet, <hi>one of the</hi> Deputy Lieutenants <hi>of the</hi> County <hi>of</hi>
Devon, <hi>and</hi> one <hi>of</hi> his Majeſties <hi>JUSTICES of</hi> the Peace <hi>of the
ſaid</hi> County, <hi>his</hi> Regiment, <hi>on</hi> Otery-hill, <hi>the</hi> 20th <hi>of</hi>
June. 1661.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LOok, do you ſee on yonder Hill,</l>
               <l>The brave bred Souldiers ſhew their skil:</l>
               <l>A royal gallant Company appear,</l>
               <l>To the Noble Colonel counted dear.</l>
               <l>They did their brave rich Colours there diſplay:</l>
               <l>Their ſtately Gallantry on a ſoul Day:</l>
               <l>But, at the laſt, the he'vens began to ſmile:</l>
               <l>And all did bleſſe, and none did them revile.</l>
               <l>The ſeveral Captains did march in ſtate:</l>
               <l>And did their Colonel congratulate.</l>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:60904:51"/>
               <l>They did there then march in brave manner,</l>
               <l>And did mount up their rich ſtately Banner.</l>
               <l>They did I ſay, their ſtately Colours ſhow:</l>
               <l>For others as well as themſelves to know:</l>
               <l>Their Feathers wag and their rich Rapiers ſhine,</l>
               <l>A Sermon preacht by a ſound rare Divine.</l>
               <l>Solid learned <hi>Aſhford</hi> was that brave man,</l>
               <l>Oh, may they his profound points duly skan.</l>
               <l>He did both duty teach of God and King,</l>
               <l>And to their joyful hearts much comfort bring.</l>
               <l>Look up brave Sonldiers ſee your <hi>Caeſars</hi> come,</l>
               <l>Advance your pikes ſhoulder musket and make rome.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe you ſaw <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A Warrier brave, a Souldier moſt compleat.</l>
               <l>Methinks I ſaw <hi>Hanibal Scipio</hi> there,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brutus, Tigranes, Tamberlain</hi> appear:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dion, Phocion,</hi> ſtout <hi>Marius,</hi> and the reſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Themiſtocles, Fabius,</hi> of Souldiers beſt.</l>
               <l>Methinks thoſe famous men I did then ſee</l>
               <l>A ſumptuous ſtately, gallant Company.</l>
               <l>To theſe brave famous men I would advance,</l>
               <l>Look on by ſtanders, ſee their Palfraies prance.</l>
               <l>In fit ſeaſon advance their Warlike Pikes,</l>
               <l>And ſee management of War like Rites.</l>
               <l>Great famous <hi>Caeſar</hi> he will come and ſee, <note place="margin">K. Charles.</note>
               </l>
               <l>You brave Gentlemen march in Your degree.</l>
               <l>Oh, had I <hi>Homers</hi> Pen to advance; Yee</l>
               <l>And write according to your Company:</l>
               <l>Of your deſert and high deſerved merit,</l>
               <l>The honour of the day which you inherit.</l>
               <l>At another time I do hope to ſee,</l>
               <l>You exerciſe your Noble Chivalry.</l>
               <l>Mean while kind Gentlemen I do <hi>you</hi> wiſh,</l>
               <l>Health and Happineſſe and Eternal bliſſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:60904:52"/>
            <head>ON MY WORTHY FRIEND, Wil. Bragge <abbr>Eſq</abbr> ONE Of the Captains belonging to the
Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Colonel, SIR <hi>JOHN DRAKE</hi> Knight and Baronet, his Regiment.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHiles that you liv'd, in Accademick Schools,</l>
               <l>It taught you to diſcern wiſemen from fools;</l>
               <l>Learning taught you deep knowledge in the Arts,</l>
               <l>Learning advanc't you, unto Noble parts.</l>
               <l>In learnings mine, you labour'd to dig deep,</l>
               <l>Advanc'd your Studyes, took the leſſer ſleep;</l>
               <l>May God Almighty, you ſleeping wakeing keep.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:60904:52"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Brave Education doth good wits Advance,</l>
               <l>Raiſe to Honour before Death leads his Dance:</l>
               <l>Ah gracious Soul hereafter Inherit,</l>
               <l>Goulden treaſures obtain by Chriſts merit:</l>
               <l>Grand Magazin of Wealth beyond compare,</l>
               <l>Eternal treaſures in the Heavens there.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Witts nimble fancy you can ſoon peirce,</l>
               <l>Ingenious men you do moſt dearly love:</l>
               <l>Learnings brave Litrature you do approve,</l>
               <l>Lightneſſe of mind though young you 'av laid aſſide.</l>
               <l>In learnings ſweetneſſe you do firm abide,</l>
               <l>Ayming at laſt to ſatiate your will:</l>
               <l>May God in's own due time your Ayme fulfill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beames of Eternal light lighten your Soul,</l>
               <l>Raiſe you above where you may ne're condole:</l>
               <l>An Angel guide you in Divineſt things,</l>
               <l>God give you favor of the King of Kings.</l>
               <l>Give you the knowledge that is high Sublime,</l>
               <l>Eternal knowledge, that is pure Divine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:60904:53"/>
            <head>ON Conſideration of our own WANTS, And my Bleſſed SAVIOURS All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>I Am in ſtraights dear Lord and now do find,</l>
               <l>A remedy fit to content my mind:</l>
               <l>My pretious Lord Chriſt doth ſupply all things,</l>
               <l>In riches far ſurpaſſing Courts of Kings.</l>
               <l>He is the grand Lord full of bright Majeſty,</l>
               <l>He's the learnedſt Dr. of Divinity.</l>
               <l>Divines doth teach to bring us unto him,</l>
               <l>He is my head, O make of me a limb.</l>
               <l>The Saints account it to be a member,</l>
               <l>Lord make me grow in grace and Glorious ſplender.</l>
               <l>What can I wiſh that thou wilt then withhold,</l>
               <l>The choiſeſt Jewels paſſing pureſt gold.</l>
               <l>Thou art my beſt Treaſure, my gold my all,</l>
               <l>In thee I live I move and ever ſhall:</l>
               <l>Thou art my life, Oh whither can I go,</l>
               <l>Out of the way from thee is but to woe.</l>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:60904:53"/>
               <l>If life I wiſh, death ſurely I ſhall find,</l>
               <l>Death hell and ſin againſt me doth combind:</l>
               <l>Open the gate that leadeth unto bliſs,</l>
               <l>On let him bleſs me that Immortal is.</l>
               <l>He is that light ye that bright glorious Sun,</l>
               <l>Who will make an end as he hath begun:</l>
               <l>He is that pretious vine that bore that grape,</l>
               <l>Who quench'd the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ſin and luſtfull rape.</l>
               <l>He is the light of truth that glorious Sun,</l>
               <l>Oh without him the world had been undone:</l>
               <l>He is the way that leadeth unto life,</l>
               <l>Out of that way it leadeth to all ſtrife.</l>
               <l>The wide broad way that leadeth unto hell,</l>
               <l>Where damned ſouls and devils there doth dwel:</l>
               <l>If ever thou doſt mean happy to be,</l>
               <l>Take care to ſerve the ſacred Trinity:</l>
               <l>The Father Son bleſt ſprite the Holy Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>Will keep all Bleſſed ſouls from being loſt.</l>
               <l>Chriſt is that Shepheard that doth keep his ſheep,</l>
               <l>He is a watchman when his ſoundly ſleep:</l>
               <l>He is our Phyſition when we are ſick,</l>
               <l>He comforts us againſt ſins mortal prick.</l>
               <l>He is that God that wonders great hath wrought,</l>
               <l>He is our deareſt friend our ſouls hath bought:</l>
               <l>He is the word that teacheth us to live,</l>
               <l>He is the Lord that doth all comforts give.</l>
               <l>He is that fair poliſh'd and corner ſtone,</l>
               <l>He is our God to whom we make our mone:</l>
               <l>He is our Saviour and ſalvation,</l>
               <l>Who ſav'd our poor ſouls from D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnation,</l>
               <l>He is that Bread of life man to preſerve,</l>
               <l>Give me thy merits not what I deſerve:</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:60904:54"/>
               <l>He is the Lyon of fair <hi>Judahs</hi> tribe,</l>
               <l>He ſent his ſpirit with us to abide:</l>
               <l>He is that ſafe and pretious way of Life,</l>
               <l>That comforts all perſons both Man and Wife.</l>
               <l>I look unto the way that leads to Bliſſe,</l>
               <l>I look unto the truth, fair truth it is.</l>
               <l>I look unto the life, that life doth give,</l>
               <l>I look to dye, and in him for to live.</l>
               <l>He is that bright and Heavenly day Starre,</l>
               <l>That guided the wiſe learned men from far.</l>
               <l>He is the ſubject of our ſacred ſtory,</l>
               <l>He is the Door that enters unto glory.</l>
               <l>If then ſo many comforts he doth bring,</l>
               <l>Let us be thankfull to our Heavenly King.</l>
               <l>I will now then conclude my mortal Storie,</l>
               <l>Praying my Soveraign, may be a Starre of Glory.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:60904:54"/>
            <head>ACCROSTICKS, ON That Rare, and Exquiſite Artiſt, <hi>GEORGE WHARTON,</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>GRand famous <hi>Wharton</hi> thou do'ſt write ſublime,</l>
               <l>End and begin of maters moſt Divine.</l>
               <l>On nature of the Starres thou mounteſt high,</l>
               <l>Rules perfect in that Art, thou canſt diſcry.</l>
               <l>God ad a Bleſſing to thy Heav'nly Art,</l>
               <l>E're happy be for what thou do'ſt impart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wiſdome and Art thou do'ſt reveal to men,</l>
               <l>High heav'nly Miſt'ries by thy learned pen:</l>
               <l>Arts hidden and Occult thou do'ſt ſet forth,</l>
               <l>Rarly expreſsing your moſt Noble worth.</l>
               <l>Things pleaſant and delightfull thou do'ſt write,</l>
               <l>On various things which doth mens minds delight;</l>
               <l>Not fit to lye hidden but ſee the light.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:60904:55"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Golden Artiſt thy Art and learned skil,</l>
               <l>E're will I love, and thy ſtately quil,</l>
               <l>Of Planets high and lofty thou cauſt tell:</l>
               <l>Range the Heavens and know where they do dwel,</l>
               <l>God give you knowledg 'bove all earthly things,</l>
               <l>E're for to live with that great King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Kings.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whiles learned <hi>Wharton</hi> doth Communicate,</l>
               <l>Heav'ns ſtately fabrick and Comenſurate:</l>
               <l>Aſtronomies learned Art to unfold,</l>
               <l>Rich and rare truths unto the world hath told.</l>
               <l>Treaſures tranſcendent maiſt thou diſcover,</l>
               <l>On famous Arts of Arts thou'rt a lover:</l>
               <l>Now learned <hi>Wharton,</hi> the beſt rules recover.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Glory after Death may your Soul obtain,</l>
               <l>Eternal happineſſe be your beſt gain:</l>
               <l>Oh maiſt thou after death aſcend on high,</l>
               <l>Raiſed up unto that Heav'nly Majeſty.</l>
               <l>God grant hereafter thou maiſt ſee his face,</l>
               <l>Enthron'd by Chriſt into a Heav'nly place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wher's nothing wanting for the ſouls content,</l>
               <l>Heav'n fills it up with divine raviſhment:</l>
               <l>After all travels paſt aſcend at laſt,</l>
               <l>Raptures to feed on divine rare repaſt.</l>
               <l>Things that tranſcend mans eye and mortal ear,</l>
               <l>On Sion hill the like doth not appear;</l>
               <l>None can Thee ſatiate but thy Saviour dear.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:60904:55"/>
            <head>ON My Worthy and Learned friend Mr. <hi>ROBERT GOMERSALL,</hi> Batchelor in DIVINITY, Late
Deceaſed.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THy Learning Language, and Rare Noble parts,</l>
               <l>Thy truth, Piety, and deſerving Arts.</l>
               <l>What is in Man, thy Braine could comprehend,</l>
               <l>Ever Real, and faithfull to thy friend.</l>
               <l>Renown'd <hi>Gomerſall,</hi> Thy name ſhall e're live,</l>
               <l>I will due praiſes to your Mem'ry give.</l>
               <l>Thou Build'ſt a Monument, to dure as long,</l>
               <l>As brave great <hi>Brytaine,</hi> ſhall not want a Tongue:</l>
               <l>For to expreſs thy worth, and Noble Fame,</l>
               <l>Still to Preſerve thy worthy Learned Name.</l>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:60904:56"/>
               <l>Thy Rich Doctrine was High, and did tranſcend,</l>
               <l>Taught Mortal man, how God might be his friend:</l>
               <l>Raiſ'd high the heart and mind did Elevate,</l>
               <l>On Divine things for to contemplate.</l>
               <l>Glory of the Age thou did'ſt live in,</l>
               <l>Brought Preſents Rare from our Heav'nly King:</l>
               <l>Theſe few lynes are thy Brave fame to Revive,</l>
               <l>Thy Books will keep the Memory alive.</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſay: As long as ſand will Run,</l>
               <l>Thy Hower Glaſs of Fame, ſhall ne're be Done.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:60904:56"/>
            <head>The AUTHORS Concluſion.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Countrymen.</salute>
            </opener>
            <lg>
               <l>EXcuſe my Lines, though they are written plain,</l>
               <l>Caſt not on them your Envy or diſdain:</l>
               <l>If that my Sov'raign Lord you do love well,</l>
               <l>Youl like my Lines for's ſake who doth excel.</l>
               <l>He's a gracious King in mercy doth abound,</l>
               <l>The like I know not where is to be found.</l>
               <l>He's humble, patient, Gentle to command,</l>
               <l>And beſt deſerves to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le this famous Land.</l>
               <l>He doth abound in meekneſs and in grace,</l>
               <l>God make me happy to ſee's bleſſed face.</l>
               <l>In Thirty Eight I kiſt his Royal Hand,</l>
               <l>By means of's Servant <hi>Monſieur le Grand:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In Moneth of June his bleſt Hand I did kiſs,</l>
               <l>All Health and Hapineſſe I do him wiſh;</l>
               <l>And pray that he may long and happy raign,</l>
               <l>And after Death in Heaven er'e remain.</l>
               <l>Let Angels then conveigh his Soul to bleſs,</l>
               <l>From Earth to Heaven's Eternal Happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:57"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60904:57"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
